<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Get Your Database Under Version Control</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/get-your-database-under-version-control/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
A little over a year ago, I wrote about <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000743.html">the importance of version control for databases</a>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
When I ask development teams whether their database is under version control, I usually get blank stares.
<p>
The database is a critical part of your application. If you deploy version 2.0 of your application against version 1.0 of your database, what do you get? A broken application, that's what. That's why <b>your database should always be under source control, right next to your application code</b>. You deploy the app, and you deploy the database. Like peanut butter and chocolate, they are two great tastes that taste great together.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="peanut butter cups: delicious peanut butter and chocolate goodness" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86dbd33970b" height="398" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/02/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86dbd33970b-pi.jpg" width="543">
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
When it comes to version control, the database is often a second or even third-class citizen. From what I've seen, teams that would <i>never</i> think of writing code without version control in a million years-- and rightly so-- can somehow be completely oblivious to the need for version control around the critical databases their applications rely on. I don't know how you can call yourself a software engineer and maintain a straight face when your database isn't under <i>exactly</i> the same rigorous level of source control as the rest of your code. Don't let this happen to you. <b>Get your database under version control</b>.
</p>
<p>
I was thinking about this again because my friend <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000971.html">and co-author</a> K. Scott Allen just wrote a brilliant five part series on the philosophy and practice of database version control:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>
<a href="http://odetocode.com/Blogs/scott/archive/2008/01/30/11702.aspx">Three rules for database work</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://odetocode.com/Blogs/scott/archive/2008/01/31/11710.aspx">The Baseline</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://odetocode.com/Blogs/scott/archive/2008/02/02/11721.aspx">Change Scripts</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://odetocode.com/Blogs/scott/archive/2008/02/02/11737.aspx">Views, Stored Procedures and the Like</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://odetocode.com/Blogs/scott/archive/2008/02/03/11746.aspx">Branching and Merging</a>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
K is one of the smartest software developers I know. Read it all; even if you currently have your database under version control (and bully for you if you do), there is much food for peanut buttery chocolatey thought here. It <b>doesn't matter what tools you use</b>-- per the <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/">agile manifesto</a>, <i>individuals and interactions are more important than processes and tools</i>. Just get your database under version control already.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-02-02T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/get-your-database-under-version-control/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
