<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Never design what you can steal</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/never-design-what-you-can-steal/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
As the old adage goes:
</p>
<blockquote><i>
good programmers write good code; great programmers steal great code.
</i></blockquote>
<p>
This is definitely true, mostly because great programmers have learned to do some research before writing anything at all. However, even great programmers tend to be <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/jeff/archive/2004/11/09/254664.aspx">absolutely terrible at graphic design</a>, even though the solution is exactly the same: <b>never design what you can steal</b>.
</p>
<p>
A prime candidate for theft is <a href="http://www.designbyfire.com/000094.html">this cheeky study in redesign</a>. It works as a funny parody of Queer Eye for the Straight Guy, but best of all, it targets <a href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/20040510.html">a page from usability guru Jakob Nielsen</a>-- who often gets a black eye for his intentionally low-tech design layouts.
</p>
<p>
I was rather skeptical of this effort at first. As a developer, <b>I sympathize with crappy layouts</b>. It's what I do! I make really crappy, basic HTML layouts. Then I fool myself into believing crappy, basic HTML layout is a good thing because it's, you know, lightweight. Like Google! But these guys made me a believer. Their redesigns were a big improvement over the original, minimalist Nielsen layout:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/20040510.html">The original Nielsen Alertbox</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.designbyfire.com/deye_web/straight_text.htm">Rewrite of the text</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.designbyfire.com/deye_web/alertbox.htm">Redesign of the web page, with illustrations</a></li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.nundroo.com/designeye/assets/quickcard.pdf">Enhanced print version</a> (pdf)</li>
</ol>
<p>
I chose not to link to the "bonus Flash enhanced" version, which was <i>not</i> an improvement.  As far as I'm concerned, the only proper use for Flash is to play <a href="http://icebox.allcharge.com/shows/show_wong/showpage.html">Mr. Wong</a> episodes.
</p>
<p>
Anyway, it was heartening to see how a few simple design changes could dramatically improve the basic HTML I regularly churn out. And if that doesn't convince you, how about this redesign of the famous <a href="http://www.airbagindustries.com/archives/002868.php">"Bin Ladin Determined To Strike in US" memo</a> that originally inspired this redesign?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2004-12-09T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/never-design-what-you-can-steal/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
