<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Introducing Stackoverflow.com</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/introducing-stackoverflow-com/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
A little over a month ago, I announced that I was <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001074.html">quitting my job</a>. But there was also something else I didn't fully announce.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
But <strong>I refuse to become a full-time blogger</strong>. I think that's a cop-out. If I look at the people I respect most in the industry, the people I view as role models-- <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html">Paul Graham</a>, <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel Spolsky</a>, <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/">Steve Yegge</a>, <a href="http://www.ericsink.com/">Eric Sink</a>, <a href="http://www.skrenta.com/">Rich Skrenta</a>, <a href="http://blog.pmarca.com/">Marc Andreesen</a>, <a href="http://www.wilshipley.com/blog/">Wil Shipley</a>, <a href="http://www.crockford.com/">Douglas Crockford</a>, <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/">Scott Guthrie</a> -- they all have one thing in common. They're not just excellent writers and communicators. <strong>They build stuff, too</strong>. The world has enough vapid commentary blogs. <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000809.html">I want to build stuff</a>-- <em>and</em> talk about it. I have a little micro-ISV startup opportunity I'll be working on, a web property I'm building out with one of the above people. I'm not ready to announce the details yet, but when I do, you'll read about it here.
</blockquote>
<p>
The "building stuff", as <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001095.html">you helped us determine</a>, is stackoverflow.com. It's a small company <strong>Joel Spolsky</strong> and I are founding together.
</p>
<p>
If you've been reading my blog for a while, you might find this pairing strange. It's true that I've been <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000679.html">critical of Joel</a> in the past. And it <em>is</em> sort of funny that I own the <a href="http://images.google.com/images?q=joel+spolsky">number one image search result</a> and <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=joel+spolsky">a top 10 search result</a> for Joel Spolsky. Good thing Joel has a sense of humor.
</p>
<p>
Occasionally I'll meet readers, or get emails from readers, who tell me that they enjoy my blog... and oh-by-the-way they strongly disagree with a few things I've said. Their phrasing clearly implies that they think there's something <em>wrong</em> with this. Well, there isn't. I'm here to tell you that <strong>occasional disagreement is healthy and normal</strong>. If you agree with everything I write here, why would you bother reading? At that point, we're the same person. I distrust people who agree with me all the time. I <em>want</em> someone to push back and encourage me to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001080.html">question my assumptions</a>.
</p>
<p>
I admire what Joel has created. He was one of the <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000077.html">earliest </a> programming bloggers, and certainly one of the first I found that helped me realize the kind of positive influence writing could have on my fellow programmers. He is very much living the dream: he founded a company with the express intent of not cashing out with VC money, but creating a sustainible place where programmers can <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000979.html">have fun while programming useful stuff</a>. It's an honor to have the opportunity to work closely with Joel, and to combine the collective power of our two communities.
</p>
<p>
So what <em>is</em> stackoverflow?
</p>
<p>
From day one, my blog has been about putting helpful information out into the world. I never had any particular aspirations for this blog to become what it is today; I'm humbled and gratified by its <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000983.html">amazing success</a>. It has quite literally changed my life. Blogs are fantastic resources, but as much as I might <a href="http://steve.yegge.googlepages.com/you-should-write-blogs">encourage my fellow programmers to blog</a>, not everyone has the time or inclination to start a blog. There's far too much great programming information trapped in forums, buried in online help, or hidden away in <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000971.html">books that nobody buys any more</a>. We'd like to unlock all that. Let's create something that makes it easy to participate, and put it online in a form that is trivially easy to find.
</p>
<p>
Are you familiar with <a href="http://everything2.com/index.pl?node_id=1441060">the movie pitch formula</a>?
</p>
<p>
<strong>Stackoverflow is sort of like the anti-<a href="http://experts-exchange.com/">experts-exchange</a> (minus the nausea-inducing sleaze and quasi-legal search engine gaming) meets <a href="http://www.wikipedia.com/">wikipedia</a> meets <a href="http://programming.reddit.com/">programming reddit</a>.</strong> It is by programmers, for programmers, with the ultimate intent of collectively increasing the sum total of <em>good</em> programming knowledge in the world. No matter what programming language you use, or what operating system you call home. Better programming is our goal.
</p>
<p>
Of course, there's more to it than that. Joel and I are <strong>recording our weekly calls and releasing them as podcasts</strong>. Listen to us describe our vision for stackoverflow in our own words -- just <a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com/">head over to stackoverflow.com</a> to download the first 46 minute episode. We're even taking questions, if you submit them in the form of audio recordings.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<script type="text/javascript">google_ad_client = &quot;pub-6424649804324178&quot;;google_ad_slot = &quot;8324348970&quot;;google_ad_width = 728;google_ad_height = 90;</script><script src="http://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/show_ads.js" type="text/javascript"></script>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-04-16T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/introducing-stackoverflow-com/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
