<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Pentium-M Home Theater PC</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/pentium-m-home-theater-pc/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I recently built a new, much lower wattage home theater PC using the Pentium-M processor. The P-M was, until very recently, a mobile-only part. And that's why it's ideal for HTPC duties-- it offers very high levels of performance at an  astonishingly modest power draw. For example, per <a href="http://techreport.com/reviews/2005q1/pentium4-600/index.x?pg=16">these system power consumption measurements at Tech-Report</a>:
</p>
<p>
Pentium 4 640 @3.2ghz<br>
125w idle, <span style="color:red">211w</span> load
</p>
<p>
Pentium-M @ 2.4ghz (overclocked)<br>
92w idle, <span style="color:red">107w</span> load
</p>
<p>
So the P-M system consumes 35% less power at idle and 97% less power at load-- while offering comparable performance. The Pentium-M is much more efficient per clock, so it doesn't <i>need</i> to run at exorbitant clock rates. There's a direct correlation between power consumption and heat/noise. The cooler a system runs, the quieter it will be. And quiet is what you want for a HTPC.
</p>
<p>
In my bench testing of the Pentium-M 1.6ghz, <b>the large, fanless Alpha heatsink never exceeded 50c under Prime95 torture test load</b>, even when left running overnight. And that's totally passive, with virtually zero directed airflow!  Try that with a Pentium 4 and you'll create your own personal <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0078966/">China Syndrome</a>. Because the P-M runs so cool, I was able to get away with using only two fans in the final system-- the power supply fan, and a dramatically undervolted 60mm exhaust fan:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Pentium-M HTPC system" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fb033970c" height="830" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/02/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fb033970c-pi.jpg" width="816">
</p>
<p>
See the three hard drives in there? Two are mounted under the DVD-R. Here's a breakdown of all the parts.
</p>
<p>
<b>Core system</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>AOpen i855GMEm mobo
</li>
<li>1.6ghz Pentium-M "Dothan" (2mb L2 cache)
</li>
<li>Alpha PAL8952 P4 heatsink
</li>
<li>Zalman northbridge cooler
</li>
<li>512mb DDR
</li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>Storage</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://www.newegg.com/app/ViewProductDesc.asp?description=22-152-014&amp;depa=0">Samsung Spinpoint 160gb</a> (3)
</li>
<li>Generic 4x DVD-R
</li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>Case</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Logisys acrylic HTPC case
</li>
<li>Sparkle 180w MicroATX power supply
</li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>Expansion cards</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://www.newegg.com/app/ViewProductDesc.asp?description=14-102-289&amp;depa=0">Radeon 9600 128mb AGP</a>, passively cooled with <a href="http://www.zalmanusa.com/usa/product/view.asp?idx=114&amp;code=013">Zalman ZM-17</a>
</li>
<li>Generic PCI 802.11 b/g adapter
</li>
<li>Hauppauge PVR-350
</li>
<li>AOpen SPDIF bracket
</li>
</ul>
<p>
The AOpen mobo offers voltage and bus speed controls; I undervolted the P-M from ~1.3v to ~1.1v, and overclocked it to 1.7ghz.  This system, as measured by my <a href="http://www.the-gadgeteer.com/killawatt-review.html">trusty Kill-a-Watt</a>, consumes 72w at windows desktop and <span style="color:red">81w</span> in <a href="http://www.mersenne.org/freesoft.htm">Prime95 torture test</a>. Now, that's power draw from the wall; due to inefficiencies in all power supplies, some of that power is immediately lost as conversion heat inside the PSU. A typical power supply is about 70 percent efficient, so the actual power consumption inside the PC is closer to <b>50w idle / <span style="color:red">57w</span> load</b>. Pretty amazing for a fully loaded 1.7ghz PC that performs like a Pentium 4 2.6ghz.
</p>
<p>
When building a quiet PC, pay close attention to the hard drives and video card you use:
</p>
<ol>
<li>Modern video cards are the <b>second largest consumer of power</b> after the CPU; I recommend the <a href="http://www.newegg.com/app/ViewProductDesc.asp?description=14-102-289&amp;depa=0">Radeon 9600</a> which is an outstanding blend of respectable DX9 performance and ultra-low power consumption. They are trivial to cool passively. Can you get a faster card? Sure, at double or triple the power budget. Do be careful to avoid the hotter running 9600XT models; 9600Pros are fine but will require a passive heatsink retrofit.
</li>
<li>
<b>Hard drives are the second loudest item in your system after the fans</b>. Unfortunately, very few hard drive manufacturers make low noise a priority, although that is slowly changing. It helps to decouple your hard drives; they are spinning significant chunks of metal at 7,200rpm. I used <a href="http://www.sorbothane.com/">sorbothane</a> in my case to soft mount the drives and damp vibration. That definitely helps, but it can't silence a fundamentally noisy drive. <b>Buy a quiet hard drive or you'll regret it</b>. I've had excellent results with the <a href="http://www.newegg.com/app/ViewProductDesc.asp?description=22-152-014&amp;depa=0">Samsung Spinpoints</a>, which are a favorite of silent PC enthusiasts.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-02-23T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/pentium-m-home-theater-pc/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
