<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Comparing GUIs: OS X vs. Windows XP</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/comparing-guis-os-x-vs-windows-xp/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
This <a href="http://www.xvsxp.com/">OS X versus Windows XP</a> site contains an <b>exhaustive, extensively illustrated 100-topic comparison of these two operating systems</b>. The author tries to be objective, which is admirable, but the extremely detailed comparison is worth reading mostly because it highlights a lot of subtle design differences. For example, this little feature of the OS X login dialog:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote><i>
Furthermore, if you type your password wrong, the login window wiggles! This simple, elegant and unintimidating feedback lets users know that they need to try again. The down side to a wiggling login screen is that it may be insufficient to notify a novice user that they entered the wrong password. A written confirmation that the password was not accepted would help novices.
</i></blockquote>
<p>
If you like comparing GUIs, you'll probably enjoy the <a href="http://www.guidebookgallery.org/index">GUIdebook</a> website, too. It's a great source of current and historic GUI screenshots. I first stumbled across this site while searching for old Excel screenshots. I didn't find any, but I did find this incredibly neat <a href="http://www.guidebookgallery.org/splashes/excel">visual comparison of every Excel splashscreen since Version 1.01</a> on the GUIdbook site. Who knew splashscreens could be so.. cool?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-10-04T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/comparing-guis-os-x-vs-windows-xp/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
