<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>The Three Faces of About Face</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-three-faces-of-about-face/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I bought my copy of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Cooper">Alan Cooper's</a> classic <b>About Face</b> in 1995. I remember poring over it, studying its excellent advice, reveling in its focus on the hot new UI paradigms standardized in Windows 95-- toolbars, menus with icons, tabbed dialogs, and so forth. Seems quaint now, if not <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000724.html">borderline obsolete</a>, but this <i>was</i> 12 whole years ago. That's almost a lifetime in computer dog-years.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<table cellpadding="4" cellspacing="4">
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1568843224/codihorr-20"><img alt="About Face cover" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877701037970c" height="384" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877701037970c-pi.png" width="300"></a>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0764526413/codihorr-20"><img alt="About Face 2.0 cover" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877701048970c" height="386" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877701048970c-pi.png" width="300"></a>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0470084111/codihorr-20"><img alt="About Face 3 cover" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a85dda05970b" height="376" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a85dda05970b-pi.png" width="300"></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1568843224/codihorr-20">About Face</a></b><br>
1995<br>
Alan Cooper
</td>
<td valign="top">
<b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0764526413/codihorr-20">About Face 2.0</a></b><br>
2003<br>
Alan Cooper, Robert Reimann
</td>
<td valign="top">
<b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0470084111/codihorr-20">About Face 3</a></b><br>
2007<br>
Alan Cooper, Robert Reimann, David Cronin
</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
I had no idea that there was a new edition of About Face until late 2003, when I saw the new cover sitting on a coworker's desk. I rushed out to get my own copy, and I found the book much improved over the original. I love Cooper, but he can be awfully bombastic at times. Having a second author dilutes Cooper's natural bombast and adds another viewpoint for a broader perspective. The new version was better and more up to date. My old copy was officially obsolete.
</p>
<p>
I was surprised to see a comment on my <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000020.html">recommended reading</a> post about yet <i>another</i> new edition of About Face released this year. Again, I rushed out to get my own copy. Cooper is obsoleting his own books at a frantic pace; it's almost as bad as software. If, like me, you're wondering <b>what's new in About Face 3</b>, there's a summary in the introduction:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>The book has been reorganized to present its ideas in a more easy-to-use reference structure. The book is divided into three parts: the first deals with process and high-level ideas about users and design, the second deals with high-level interaction design principles, and the third deals with lower-level interface design principles
</li>
<li>The first part describes the <a href="http://media.wiley.com/product_data/excerpt/13/07645264/0764526413.pdf">Goal-Directed Design process</a> (pdf) in much greater detail than in the second edition, and more accurately reflects current practices at <a href="http://www.cooper.com/">Cooper</a>, including research techniques, the creation of personas, and how to use personas and scenarios to synthesize interaction design solutions.
</li>
<li>Throughout the book, we attempt to more explicitly discuss visual interface design concepts, methods and issues, as well as issues related to a number of platforms beyond the desktop.
</li>
<li>Terminology and examples in the book have been updated to reflect the current state of the art in the industry, and the text as a whole has been thoroughly edited to improve clarity and readability.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
I'll vouch for the readability improvement in text and layout -- this is a much better designed book overall. Adding the third author has improved the book even more, definitively obsoleting the previous version. <b>About Face 3 is the best edition of this classic yet</b>. If you've never owned a copy, consider yourself lucky on two counts:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>You don't have to waste money on old editions; you can start with the latest and best edition.
</li>
<li>You're about to read one of the best books ever written on interaction design. Enjoy.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
I envy the experience you're about to have. For the rest of us, time to pony up the upgrade fee. Again.
</p>
<p>
If you like About Face, you'll also enjoy Cooper's <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0672326140/codihorr-20">The Inmates Are Running The Asylum</a>. Originally released in 1999, it was similarly refreshed with a second edition in 2004. I own the first edition, so it looks like I'll be upgrading, too.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-06-28T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-three-faces-of-about-face/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
