<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>See You at MIX08!</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/see-you-at-mix08/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Well, you won't technically see <i>me</i> at <a href="http://visitmix.com/2008/">MIX08</a> this year. But you will see some <a href="http://www.vertigo.com/mix">very cool top-secret stuff Vertigo created</a> in the keynote.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://visitmix.com/2008/"><img alt="mix08 logo" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86dbc1b970b" height="216" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/03/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86dbc1b970b-pi.png" width="223"></a>
</p>
<p>
<b>MIX is by far my favorite Microsoft conference</b> after attending the '06 and '07 iterations. And not just because this year they have <a href="http://visitmix.com/blogs/News/437/">a Rock Band competition</a>* and <a href="http://visitmix.com/blogs/News/The-King-of-Kongs-Steve-Wiebe-joins-MIX08-for-a-special-screening-of-the-movie-and-an-attempt-to-rec/">a screening of The King of Kong with star Steve Wiebe</a>. Oh, and did I mention the exclusive MIX party at <a href="http://www.taolasvegas.com/">the Tao nightclub</a>? These things certainly don't hurt.
</p>
<p>
What I love about Mix is that it ...
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>is relatively small and intimate, at around 2,000 attendees.
</li>
<li>seamlessly merges software engineering and design.
</li>
<li>includes a lot of non-Microsoft folks, even those that are traditionally hostile to Microsoft, so there's plenty of perspective.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
And it's in Las Vegas. Although I find gambling dreadfully boring (hey, maybe <i>that's</i> another reason why <a href="http://twitter.com/codinghorror/statuses/766773242">I never got into World of Warcraft</a>), there's always something fun to do.
</p>
<p>
If you work in the Microsoft stack, and any of that sounds even vaguely interesting -- <b>sign up for next year's MIX</b> when you can. You won't be disappointed. In fact, I guarantee satisfaction. If you attend MIX and don't thoroughly enjoy the experience, then I dare say there's something wrong with <i>you</i>.
</p>
<p>
A team at Vertigo has been working at breakneck pace over the last two months to <b>build something extra-special that will be shown in the MIX keynote</b>. Of course I can't talk about it until the actual keynote Wednesday morning, but I will give you this one hint: it invokes the power of <i>rock</i>. Details will be available on <a href="http://www.vertigo.com/mix.aspx">Vertigo's MIX page</a> in time with the keynote.
</p>
<p>
Our fearless leader, <a href="http://blogs.vertigo.com/personal/scott/Blog/default.aspx">Scott Stanfield</a>, will also be delivering a blacklisted MIX session on Friday, which expands on what we're showing in the keynote. Be sure to mark this one on your calendar if you're in attendance.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="mix08: Vertigo's blacklisted session" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86dbc48970b" height="465" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/03/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86dbc48970b-pi.png" width="635">
</p>
<p>
I've been specifically told <i>"it'll be epic; wear your pampers."</i> Duly noted.
</p>
<p>
* Which Vertigo is <i>totally</i> going to win. You read it here first.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-03-05T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/see-you-at-mix08/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
