<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Firefox as an IDE</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/firefox-as-an-ide/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Although <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000789.html">I prefer IE7's native speed and feel</a> for day-to-day browsing chores, there's no doubt that <b>Firefox is my primary web development IDE</b>.
</p>
<p>
Whenever I need to troubleshoot HTML, CSS, or JavaScript, I immediately reach for Firefox. That's primarily because of two incredibly powerful developer extensions for Firefox:
</p>
<p>
<b>1. <a href="http://chrispederick.com/work/webdeveloper/">Web Developer Extension</a></b>
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Firefox Web Developer Extension screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877700667970c" height="628" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/04/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877700667970c-pi.png" width="589">
</p>
<p>
WDE has lots of useful features, but the most wonderful thing about WDE is that <b>everything is editable in real-time</b>. Edit the CSS, edit the HTML, and watch your changes take effect as you type. It's like magic.
</p>
<p>
<b>2. <a href="http://www.getfirebug.com/">Firebug</a></b>
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Firefox Firebug screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877700673970c" height="581" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/04/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877700673970c-pi.png" width="714">
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.getfirebug.com/">Firebug</a> is a richer tool than WDE; it goes far beyond real-time editing of HTML and CSS, and delves deeply into profiling and debugging JavaScript. It also offers metrics on download time and download order over the wire. I highly recommend checking out <a href="http://ajaxian.com/archives/joe-hewitt-firebug-power-user-demo">the Joe Hewitt Firebug power user demo movie</a> to get a sense of its full feature set.
</p>
<p>
I can't imagine debugging a web app without these two essential tools, which <b>transform Firefox into the Visual Studio of browsers</b>. It'd be akin to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000195.html">writing a .NET application in Notepad</a>. In fact, I feel so strongly about the utility of these extensions that I'm stopping to donate $10 to each project, right now. This is part of <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000735.html">my ongoing monthly contribution to small software vendors</a>.
</p>
<p>
If you haven't used these tools yet, I envy the experience you're about to have. Download them both and start experimenting. If you have used Firebug and WDE, I encourage you to share your favorite tips in the comments.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-04-04T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/firefox-as-an-ide/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
