<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>What's on Your Keychain.. in 2006?</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/whats-on-your-keychain-in-2006/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
A little over a year ago, I documented what was <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000251.html">on my keychain</a>. Here's what I have today:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="What's on my keychain in 2006" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd1aa970c" height="307" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd1aa970c-pi.jpg" width="401">
</p>
<p>
If you're troubled by what appears to be profanity on the <a href="http://www.leatherman.com/products/tools/s4/default.asp">Leatherman Squirt</a>, I'll refer you to my <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000251.html">previous post</a>-- it's a <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0110912/">Pulp Fiction</a> joke. This amazing little <b>pocket knife</b> is the only item that I haven't changed since 2005. I use it all the time, mostly for its scissors, screwdriver, or knife functionality (in that order). It sure does come in handy-- <a href="http://www.mikepope.com/blog/DisplayBlog.aspx?permalink=1517">bricolage</a> in action!
</p>
<p>
<b>USB flash drives</b> are a dime a dozen these days. <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000215.html">It's the new floppy disk</a>. This particular flash drive is a 1 gigabyte <a href="http://www.iomega.com/direct/products/family.jsp?FOLDER%3C%3Efolder_id=27075041&amp;ASSORTMENT%3C%3East_id=26890319&amp;bmUID=1150003983671">Iomega Micro Mini</a>. It's by far my favorite USB flash drive model, for two key reasons:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>It's really, really small. Tiny, even.
</li>
<li>The end cap is physically attached to the drive; rotate it to expose the usb interface.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
So many USB flash drives have end caps that aren't physically attached to the drive. The first thing I do is lose them! The Mini's design cleverly solves this problem. There's even a little cutout so you can see the drive activity LED with the cap rotated.
</p>
<p>
The ARC <b>LED AAA battery flashlight</b> I used to carry sadly died. And the company that made it isn't around any more. But the replacement is even better-- the <a href="http://www.dansdata.com/peakled.htm">Peak LED Matterhorn</a>. Here's why:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>It has three LEDs instead of a single LED. It's much brighter.
</li>
<li>The lanyard attachment point screws apart, so it can be easily detached from the keychain.
</li>
<li>The runtime profile of the three-LED model is superior: seven hours before it drops to half its original brightness.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
It is a wee bit longer, but otherwise it's a much welcomed improvement over the ARC. I stuck with the basic black keychain model, but there are a <a href="http://www.peakledsolutions.net/aaa.html">variety of styles to choose from</a>.
</p>
<p>
The one item I wish I had on my keychain is a <b>pen</b>. I haven't been able to find anything appropriately compact and portable. Dan carries a <a href="http://www.dansdata.com/inka.htm">space pen</a>, but I need something that'll attach to a keyring.
</p>
<p>
I should mention that I do, in fact, carry <i>keys</i> on my keychain as well. I just removed them in the photo to highlight the important stuff.
</p>
<p>
So what's on <i>your</i> keychain?
</p>
<p>
<font color="red">update</font>: Here's my <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001036.html">2008 edition of the keychain</a>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-06-08T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/whats-on-your-keychain-in-2006/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
