<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Software Pricing: Are We Doing It Wrong?</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/software-pricing-are-we-doing-it-wrong/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
One of the side effects of <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001280.html">using the iPhone App store so much</a> is that it's started to fundamentally alter my perception of software pricing. So many excellent iPhone applications are either free, or no more than a few bucks at most. That's below the threshold of impulse purchase and squarely in no-brainer territory for anything decent that I happen to be interested in.
</p>
<p>
But applications that cost $5 or more? <i>Outrageous! Highway robbery!</i>
</p>
<p>
This is all very strange, as a guy who is used to spending at least $30 for software of any consequence whatsoever. I love <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000735.html">supporting my fellow software developers with my wallet</a>, and the iPhone App Store has never made that easier.
</p>
<p>
While there's an <a href="http://mashable.com/2009/07/21/iphone-app-race-bottom/">odd aspect of race to the bottom</a> that I'm not sure is entirely healthy for the iPhone app ecosystem, the idea that <b>software should be priced low enough to pass the average user's "why not" threshold</b> is a powerful one.
</p>
<p>
What I think isn't well understood here is that low prices can be a force multiplier all out of proportion to the absolute reduction in price. Valve software has been aggressively experimenting in this area; consider the <a href="http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/57308">example of the game Left 4 Dead</a>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
Valve co-founder Gabe Newell announced during a DICE keynote today that last weekend's half-price sale of Left 4 Dead resulted in a 3000% increase in sales of the game, posting overall sales (in dollar amount) that beat the title's original launch performance.
</blockquote>
<p>
It's sobering to think that cutting the price in half, months later, made <i>more</i> money for Valve in total than launching the game at its original $49.95 price point. (And, incidentally, that's the price I paid for it. No worries, I got my fifty bucks worth of gameplay out of this excellent game months ago.)
</p>
<p>
The experiments didn't end there. Observe the utterly non-linear scale at work as the price of software is experimentally reduced even further on their <a href="http://store.steampowered.com/">Steam</a> network:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
The massive <a href="http://store.steampowered.com/">Steam</a> holiday sale was also a big win for Valve and its partners. The following holiday sales data was released, showing the sales breakdown organized by price reduction:
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>10% sale = 35% increase in sales (<b>real dollars</b>, not units shipped)
</li>
<li>25% sale = 245% increase in sales
</li>
<li>50% sale = 320% increase in sales
</li>
<li>75% sale = 1470% increase in sales
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>
Note that <i>these are total dollar sale amounts!</i> Let's use some fake numbers to illustrate how dramatic the difference really is. Let's say our hypothetical game costs $40, and we sold <b>100 copies</b> of it at that price.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<table cellpadding="4" cellspacing="4" width="400">
<tr>
<td>Original price</td>
<td>Discount</td>
<td>Sale Price</td>
<td align="right">Total Sales</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>$40</td>
<td>none</td>
<td>$40</td>
<td align="right">$4,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>$40</td>
<td>10%</td>
<td>$36</td>
<td align="right">$5,400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>$40</td>
<td>25%</td>
<td>$30</td>
<td align="right">$9,800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>$40</td>
<td>50%</td>
<td>$20</td>
<td align="right">$12,800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>$40</td>
<td>75%</td>
<td>$10</td>
<td align="right">$58,800</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
If this pattern Valve documented holds true, and if my experience on the iPhone App store is any indication, <b>we've been doing software pricing completely wrong</b>. At least <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000995.html">for digitally distributed software</a>, anyway.
</p>
<p>
In particular, I've always felt that Microsoft has priced their operating system upgrades far, far too high -- and would have sold a <i>ton</i> more licenses if they had sold them at the "heck, why not?" level. For example, take a look at these upgrade options:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<table cellpadding="4" cellspacing="4" width="400">
<tr>
<td><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001AMHWP8/?tag=codihorr-20">Mac OS X 10.6 Upgrade</a></td>
<td align="right">$29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B002DHLUWK/?tag=codihorr-20">Microsoft Windows 7 Home Premium Upgrade</a></td>
<td align="right">$119</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
Putting aside <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000796.html">schoolyard OS rivalries</a> for a moment, which one of these would you be more likely to buy? I realize this isn't entirely a fair comparison, so if $29 seems as bonkers to you as an application for 99 cents -- which I'd argue is much less crazy than it sounds -- then fine. Say the Windows 7 upgrade price was a more rational $49, or $69. I'm sure the thought of that drives the Redmond <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001283.html">consumer surplus capturing marketing weasels</a> apoplectic. But the Valve data -- and my own gut intuition -- leads me to believe that they'd actually make <i>more</i> money if they priced their software at the "why not?" level.
</p>
<p>
I'm not saying these pricing rules should apply to <i>every</i> market and <i>every</i> type of software in the world. But for software sold in high volumes to a large audience, I believe they might. At the very least, if you sell software, you might consider experimenting with pricing, as Valve has. You could be pleasantly surprised.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000735.html">I love buying software</a>, and I know I buy a <i>heck</i> of a lot more of it when it's priced right. So why not?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2009-08-05T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/software-pricing-are-we-doing-it-wrong/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
