<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Invisible Formatting Tags are Evil</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/invisible-formatting-tags-are-evil/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
So I'm merrily editing my document in Word, or the WYSWYG editor of my choice, and <b>I accidentally delete one of the invisible formatting tags embedded in the document</b>. Carnage ensues. Here's an example from Outlook:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Small GIF movie demo of hidden formatting codes" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd5e0970c" height="436" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd5e0970c-pi.gif" width="584">
</p>
<p>
It's enough to drive me absolutely bonkers. And it happens all the time. Not to put too fine a point on it, but <b>the problem with invisible formatting tags is that they're, well, <i>invisible</i>.</b>
</p>
<p>
I'm not against WYSIWYG editors, but at least <b>give us a way to optionally reveal the formatting tags in the document</b> so I can tell what the heck I'm deleting. You know, <i>before</i> I destroy the formatting in the document. I can't even begin to tell you how many times I've been utterly dumbfounded by the effects of an innocuous edit in Microsoft Word-- just because I happened to overwrite the wrong invisible formatting tag. Thank goodness for my old friend, CTRL+Z, but editing a Word document is a nerve wracking experience not unlike walking through a field of formatting land mines.
</p>
<p>
I've grown to dislike the rather severe limitations of browser-based WYSIWYG editors like <a href="http://freetextbox.com/demos/">FreeTextBox</a>, too, but at least they allow you to make the formatting tags visible by switching to HTML view.
</p>
<p>
I like my markup clean, simple, and most of all-- visible. Maybe I'm too old school for my own good, but I now prefer to edit my blog posts in a plain textbox, or possibly in the Visual Studio HTML editor for colorization and intellisense support.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-05-08T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/invisible-formatting-tags-are-evil/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
