<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Headphone Snobbery</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/headphone-snobbery/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I've talked about all <b>the essential environmental things a programmer should have</b>: a <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/investing-in-a-quality-programming-chair/">good chair</a>, at least <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/does-more-than-one-monitor-improve-productivity/">two monitors</a>, and a <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/the-keyboard-cult/">great keyboard</a>.
</p>
<p>
One thing I haven't talked about, though, is headphones. Headphones are probably the most optional item in that list. But <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/the-programmers-bill-of-rights/">if you're not blessed with a quiet workplace</a>, they can be essential. There are lots of great choices in headphones, but the set I own and recommend is the <a href="http://www.headphone.com/products/headphones/all-headphones/sennheiser-hd-580.php">Sennheiser 580</a>.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.headphone.com/products/headphones/all-headphones/sennheiser-hd-580.php"><img alt="Sennheiser 580 Headphones" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd8d7970c" height="283" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd8d7970c-pi.jpg" width="188"></a>
</p>
<p>
<b>Am I really advocating spending two hundred dollars on a set of headpones?</b> <i>Yes. Yes I am.</i> Now, <a href="http://www.headphone.com/guide/by-manufacturer/akg/akg-k-1000.php">you could spend a lot more</a>. This is about extracting the maximum bang for your buck:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Unlike your computer, or your car, your headphones will never wear out or become obsolete. I hesitate to say lifetime, but they're multiple decade investments at the very least.
</li>
<li>The number one item that affects the music you hear is the speakers. Without a good set of headphones, everything else is irrelevant.
</li>
<li>The right headphones can deliver sound equivalent to extremely high-end floorstanding speakers worth thousands of dollars.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
If you're the type of person who is perfectly happy listening to 64 kilobit MP3s through a $5 set of beige headphones, that's fine. There's nothing wrong with that. Keep on scrolling; this post is not for you.
</p>
<p>
But if you're any kind of music enthusiast, or you work in noisy environments, a quality set of headphones will be one of the best $200 investments you could possibly make.
</p>
<p>
I'm a big fan of the guys at <a href="http://www.headphone.com/">HeadRoom</a>; not only are they a reputable vendor, they're a great source for <a href="http://www.headphone.com/collections/top-10-headphones">unbiased information about headphones in general</a>. You don't have to buy anything there, but it's definitely the first place you should start.
</p>
<p>
If you become a minor headphone enthusiast like myself, you might also want to <b>invest in an inexpensive external headphone amplifier</b>. It's not required by any means, but after a nice set of headphones, it can have the second biggest effect on the resulting sound you hear. The coolest model for computer geeks is the <a href="http://www.headphone.com/products/headphone-amps/the-mobile-line/headroom-bithead.php">HeadRoom BitHead</a>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
Take a BitHead, plug it into the USB port on your computer, then plug the best headphones you've got into the BitHead, and BAM, knock-your-socks-off sound. Then later, pack it up in a HeadRoom bag with your favorite portable player, and you've got one of the most aurally delightful portable audio systems on the planet. Think about it: a great back end for your computer and a sweet analog headphone amp to use with your portable player for only $199. Your ears will thank you.
<p>
The BitHead has a bit of a split personality: it is a battery powered miniature headphone amp for use with portable players. And it's a USB powered external sound card and headphone amp for computers.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Dan has a good <a href="http://www.dansdata.com/bithead.htm">review of the BitHead</a> which goes into more depth. It garners a "highly recommended" from him and from me.
</p>
<p>
As far as I'm concerned, wires are the way to go for headphones. But if you demand freedom from the tyranny of wires, maybe these <a href="http://www.headphone.com/guide/by-manufacturer/sennheiser/sennheiser-rs-65-wireless.php">Sennheiser 65 wireless headphones</a> are more your speed. If wireless is your bag, bear in mind that you need to be extra careful in this category-- wireless transmission isn't exactly synonymous with quality.
</p>
<p>
At the risk of sounding like a total Sennheiser shill, if you need a headset/microphone combination for things like Skype, <a href="http://www.dansdata.com/s140150.htm">the Sennheiser PC150 is passable and inexpensive</a>. But the audio quality and comfort is nowhere near what you'll get out of the HD580s.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-12-08T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/headphone-snobbery/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
