<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Return to the Planet of Managed Code Bloat</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/return-to-the-planet-of-managed-code-bloat/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I just updated my post <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000271.html">The Bloated World of Managed Code</a> with baseline memory footprints for Console and Winforms apps in .NET 2.0.
</p>
<p>
I'll admit <b>I am a bit of a hypocrite when it comes to managed code apps</b>. Now that tiny, native BitTorrent clients are available such as <a href="http://www.utorrent.com/">uTorrent</a> and <a href="http://www.bitcomet.com/">BitComet</a>, I just can't force myself to suffer through the Java (<a href="http://azureus.sourceforge.net/">Azeureus</a>) and Python (<a href="http://pingpong-abc.sourceforge.net/">ABC</a>) clients. They're nice enough, but I want small, clean and fast for this kind of app. And where's the .NET BitTorrent client, anyway?
</p>
<p>
Managed code can be <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000234.html">plenty</a> <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000299.html">fast</a>, but I've always said that <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000366.html">managed code isn't appropriate for every kind of application</a>. It's another tool in your toolbox, but not the only one.
</p>
<p>
One particularly egregious example of <b>managed code misuse</b>, however, is in <a href="http://www.anandtech.com/video/showdoc.aspx?i=2188&amp;p=2">ATI's Catalyst video card drivers</a>. The "control center" is a client app which allows you to manipulate the settings. It's written in .NET 1.1 and launched via a button in the graphics driver tab.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="ATI Catalyst launcher" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd705970c" height="376" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/01/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd705970c-pi.jpg" width="313">
</p>
<p>
It's a reasonable <i>concept</i>, but in practice-- it sucks. Even on a clean Pentium 4 3.2 machine with 1gb of RAM, loading the control center for the first time feels like almost a full minute of waiting for something to happen. As <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/junfeng/archive/2004/09/19/231628.aspx">commenters on Junfeng Zhang's log point out</a>, this is likely due more to poor coding than anything else. But what really irks me is that <b>all I want to do is adjust a few minor video card settings</b>. Is it really appropriate to have such a heavyweight app for such a simple task?
</p>
<p>
Which brings me back to using managed code in appropriate places. Although there was a bit of a hubbub <a href="http://www.microsoft-watch.com/article2/0,1995,1820607,00.asp">about managed code and Vista last year</a>, Microsoft is pursuing managed code aggressively, as Dan Fernandez notes in <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/danielfe/archive/2005/12/16/504847.aspx">Debunking the Microsoft's not using Manged Code Myth</a>. He provides a succinct list of recent Microsoft products and the number of lines of managed code in each one:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Visual Studio 2005: 7.5 million lines
</li>
<li>SQL Server 2005: 3 million lines
</li>
<li>BizTalk Server: 2 million lines
</li>
<li>Visual Studio Team System: 1.7 million lines
</li>
<li>Windows Presentation Foundation: 900K lines
</li>
<li>Windows Sharepoint Services: 750K lines
</li>
<li>Expression Interactive Designer: 250K lines
</li>
<li>Sharepoint Portal Server: 200K lines
</li>
<li>Content Management Server: 100K lines
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Managed code is great. But a world where everything is managed code-- including the operating system and essential utilities-- is still pretty far off.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-01-11T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/return-to-the-planet-of-managed-code-bloat/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
