<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>But You Did Not Persuade Me</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/but-you-did-not-persuade-me/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>One of my favorite movie scenes is from <a href="http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/last_king_of_scotland/">The Last King of Scotland</a>, a dramatized "biography" of the megalomaniac dictator <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idi_Amin">Idi Amin</a>, as seen through the eyes of a fictional Scottish personal physician.</p>
<video poster="/content/images/2015/08/you-did-not-persuade-me-thumbnail.jpg" width="100%" height="242" preload="none" controls>
<source src="http://discourse-cdn.codinghorror.com/uploads/default/original/3X/9/5/954ba00bb034b1893024892e0a2e2bf7eb29e3a6.mp4">
</source></video>
<blockquote>
<table>
<tr>
<td style="width:100px" valign="top">Idi Amin</td>
<td valign="top">I want you to tell me what to do!</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Garrigan</td>
<td valign="top">You want ME to tell YOU what to do?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Amin</td>
<td valign="top">Yes, you are my advisor. You are the only one I can trust in here. <i>You should have told me not to throw the Asians out, in the first place!</i>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Garrigan</td>
<td valign="top"><i>I DID!</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">Amin</td>
<td valign="top">But you did not persuade me, Nicholas. You did <i>not persuade me!</i>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</blockquote>
<p>If you haven't watched this movie yet, you should. It is amazing. (For trivia buffs, this is the video clip that prompted me to write <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2010/09/youtube-vs-fair-use.html">YouTube vs. Fair Use</a>. I eventually switched to hosting it locally using <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/video">the HTML5 video tag</a>.)</p>
<p>What I love about this tour de force of a scene – beyond the incredible acting – is that it illustrates just how powerful of a force persuasion really is. In the hands of a madman or demagogue, dangerously powerful. Hopefully you don't deal with too many insane dictators on a daily basis, but the reason this scene works so well is the unavoidable truth it exposes: <b>to have any hope of influencing others, <i>you must be able to persuade them</i>.</b></p>
<p>Steve Yegge is as accomplished a software engineer as I can think of. I was amazed to hear him tell us repeatedly and at length on a podcast that <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2008/10/the-one-thing-every-software-engineer-should-know.html">the one thing every software engineer should know</a> is not how to write amazing code, but how to market themselves and their project. What is marketing except <i>persuasion?</i></p>
<p>Marc Hedlund, who founded Wesabe and is now the VP of Engineering at Etsy, thinks of himself not as a CEO or boss, but as the <a href="http://radar.oreilly.com/2006/12/engineering-management-hacks-e-1.html">Lobbyist-in-Chief</a>. I believe that could be re-written as Persuader-in-Chief with no loss of meaning or nuance.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I was recently asked how I run our development team. I said, “Well, <b>basically I blog about something I think we should do, and if the blog post convinces the developers, they do it. If not, I lobby for it, and if that fails too, the idea falls on the floor.</b> They need my approval to launch something, but that’s it. That’s as much ‘running things’ as I do, and most of the ideas come from other people at this point, not from me and my blog posts. I’ve argued against some of our most successful ideas, so it’s a good thing I don’t try to exert more control.”</p>
<p>I’m exaggerating somewhat; of course I haven’t blogged about all of our ideas yet. But I do think of myself as Lobbyist-in-Chief, and I have lots of good examples of cases where I failed to talk people into an idea and it didn’t happen as a result. One person I said this to asked, “So who holds the product vision, then?” and I replied, “Well, I guess I do,” but really that’s not right. We all do. The product is the result of the ideas that together we’ve agreed to pursue. I recruit people based on their interest in and enthusiasm about the ideas behind Wesabe, and then set them loose, and we all talk and listen constantly. That’s how it works — and believe it or not, it does work.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So how do we persuade? Primarily, I think, when we <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/08/leading-by-example.html">lead by example</a>. Even if that means getting down on your knees and <a href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/20081201/how-hard-could-it-be-my-style-of-servant-leadership.html">cleaning a toilet</a> to show someone else how it's done. But maybe you're not a leader. Maybe you're just a lowly peon. Even as a peon, it's still possible to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2006/09/changing-your-organization-for-peons.html">persuade your team and those around you</a>. A commenter summarized this grassroots method of persuasion nicely:</p>
<ul>
<li>His ideas were, on the whole, pretty good.</li>
<li>He worked mostly bottom-up rather than top-down.</li>
<li>He worked to gain the trust of others first by dogfooding his own recommendations before pushing them on others.</li>
<li>He was patient and waited for the wheels to turn.</li>
</ul>
<p>Science and data are among the best ways to be objectively persuasive, but remember that data alone isn't the reductionist end of every single topic. Beware the <a href="http://stopdesign.com/archive/2009/03/20/goodbye-google.html">41 shades of blue</a> pitfall.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Yes, it’s true that a team at Google couldn’t decide between two blues, so they’re testing 41 shades between each blue to see which one performs better. I had a recent debate over whether a border should be 3, 4 or 5 pixels wide, and was asked to prove my case. I can’t operate in an environment like that. I’ve grown tired of debating such minuscule design decisions. There are more exciting design problems in this world to tackle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If I measure by click data alone, <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2009/07/how-not-to-advertise-on-the-internet.html">all Internet advertising should have breasts in it</a>. Incorporate data, by all means. But you need to tell a bigger, grander, more inspiring story than that to be truly <i>persuasive</i>.</p>
<p>I <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/07/whatever-happened-to-civility-on-the-internet.html">re-read Letter from a Birmingham Jail</a> every year because I believe it is the single best persuasive essay I've ever read. It is remarkably persuasive without ever resorting to anger, incivility, or invective. <a href="http://www.africa.upenn.edu/Articles_Gen/Letter_Birmingham.html">Read it now</a>. But do more than just read; <i>study</i> it. How does it work? Why does it work? Does it cite any data? What techniques make this essay so incredibly compelling?</p>
<p><a href="http://www.africa.upenn.edu/Articles_Gen/Letter_Birmingham.html"><img alt="Letter-from-birmingham-jail" title="Letter-from-birmingham-jail" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2012/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b0177438da35e970d-pi.jpg" width="300" height="406"></a></p>
<p>Nobody ever changed anything by remaining quiet, idly standing by, or blending into the faceless, voiceless masses. If you ever want to effect change, in your work, in your life, <b>you must learn to persuade others</b>.</p>
<table>
<tr><td class="welovecodinghorror">
[advertisement] How are you showing off your awesome? Create a <a href="http://careers.stackoverflow.com/cv" rel="nofollow">Stack Overflow Careers profile</a> and show off all of your hard work from Stack Overflow, Github, and virtually every other coding site. Who knows, you might even get recruited for a great <a href="http://careers.stackoverflow.com/jobs" rel="nofollow">new position</a>!
</td></tr>
</table>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2012-07-23T13:11:42.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/but-you-did-not-persuade-me/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
