<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>The Story of SkiFree</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-story-of-skifree/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Laurent Bourgeois sent in an amusing link to <a href="http://ski.ihoc.net/">the story of SkiFree</a> in the words of Chris Pirih, the original Microsoft programmer who wrote it:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
I wrote SkiFree in C on my home computer, entirely for my own education and entertainment. One day while I was playing with it at work, the program manager for Windows Entertainment Pack happened to look over my shoulder and immediately decided he had to have this game. I called it WinSki, but the Microsoft marketroids hated that and decided, for inscrutible marketroidal reasons, to call it SkiFree. After some token resistance I let them have their way. Since the program was not originally a Microsoft product, Microsoft licensed it from me and paid me some trivial one-time fee (something like 100 shares of MSFT stock, no royalties) for its use.
<p>
SkiFree was intended to run on a 386 PC with VGA display. Such computers were not very powerful, nothing like modern PCs that can do 3-D rendering at millions of textured polygons per second.... No, in those days there wasn't even any such thing as a "video accelerator" -- the VGA was just a dumb pixel buffer hanging off the excruciatingly slow ISA bus. This made it pretty challenging to get good performance out of even simple sprite-oriented animation! Windows didn't help matters any by introducing several layers of abstraction between the program and the video hardware.... I discovered that it was worth almost any amount of preprocessing (on the "fast" 386 CPU) to reduce the amount of video I/O (over the slow ISA), so I designed a fairly clever algorithm to combine overlapping objects/erasures and blt minimal regions in each frame. The result was perfectly flicker-free transparent sprite animation at reasonable speed even on very slow computers, such as an old 286/EGA machine I found in the testing lab. Nowadays one would probably just render the sprites back-to-front in a memory buffer and blt the entire window on each frame.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Chris kindly provides an updated 32-bit version of SkiFree on his page as well.
</p>
<p>
I definitely remember SkiFree from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Entertainment_Pack">Windows Entertainment Pack</a>. What's particularly scary is that many of these games have <b>their own highly detailed Wikipedia pages already</b>-- including <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SkiFree">a page on SkiFree</a>. The infinite monkeys have been busy!
</p>
<p>
Evidently SkiFree evolved from an earlier text-mode skiing game Chris wrote for a VAX:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Text mode SkiFree for a VAX" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67ca970b" height="303" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67ca970b-pi.png" width="378">
</p>
<p>
And it was influenced by <a href="http://www.atariage.com/software_page.html?SoftwareID=1280">Activision's Atari 2600 Skiing cartridge</a>:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Activision Skiing for the Atari 2600" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67e1970b" height="239" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67e1970b-pi.png" width="346">
</p>
<p>
Which brings us to the venerable SkiFree-- <b>Windows 3.0 gaming at its finest</b>.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Screenshot of SkiFree for Windows" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67f2970b" height="283" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67f2970b-pi.png" width="332">
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-12-18T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-story-of-skifree/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
