<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Our Fractured Online Identities</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/our-fractured-online-identities/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
<a href="http://www.dashes.com/anil/">Anil Dash</a> has been blogging since 1999. He's a member of the Movable Type team from the earliest days. As you'd expect from a man who has lived in the trenches for so long, his blog is excellent. It's well worth a visit if you haven't been there already. I was recently reading through <a href="http://www.dashes.com/anil/2002/09/some-commendati.html">his 2002 blog recommendations</a> and marvelling at the hardy few who survived through five long years of the internet. The way I figure, that's equivalent to thirty-five people years.
</p>
<p>
I also noticed something interesting lodged in the sidebar of his blog. A long list of Anil Dash's <b>many online identities</b>, spread across no less than 29 different websites:
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.dashes.com/anil/"><img alt="Anil Dash's many online identities" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877703912970c" height="260" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877703912970c-pi.png" width="514"></a>
</p>
<p>
Laurel Krahn created one of the first 30 weblogs back in 1998. Her <a href="http://www.laurelkrahn.net/">home page</a> paints a similarly <b>fractured picture of her online identity</b>. I count 21 different websites that represent some part of Laurel:
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.laurelkrahn.net/"><img alt="Laurel Krahn's many online identities" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877703916970c" height="276" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877703916970c-pi.png" width="501"></a>
</p>
<p>
There's no way any one person could truly keep these 20 or 30 websites up to date. So which one of these websites represents the <i>real</i> Laurel Krahn, the <i>real</i> Anil Dash? Or do all these tiny fragments of identity cumulatively sum to a whole? Browsing around their sites, it's fairly easy to determine what is getting the lion's share of attention, and pare away the neglected parts. Still, it's unclear.
</p>
<p>
I suppose my online identity is similarly fractured, although somewhat less so than Anil and Laurel. I obviously have this primary blog, which represents me professionally. But I also have a <a href="http://twitter.com/codinghorror">twitter stream</a>, which I alternately treat as my inner monologue, a link blog, and as a <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000840.html">form of public instant messaging</a>. Then there are my Vertigo blogs, a handful of online games I play semi-frequently, and various other online forums that I regularly participate in for particular special interests. All these things are me.
</p>
<p>
But which one is the <i>real</i> me? Is my online identity even a reasonable approximation of who I am? I think it could be. What you read here is mostly what you get, minus some corner-case peculiarities that probably aren't interesting to anyone but me (and my wife, but she's bound by law). It's reassuring to have a single central authoritative place that represents <i>me</i> online.
</p>
<p>
Mostly, <b>I'm just amazed that these veteran bloggers feel they can actually maintain twenty or thirty different facets of their identity across all those disparate websites</b>. I certainly can't. I struggle to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000983.html">write one lousy blog four to five times a week</a>. I'm more interested in shrinking my focus into an ever narrower and sharper point than I am in diluting my effort across dozens of different websites.
</p>
<p>
There's no right or wrong answer here, of course. You should follow your interests wherever they lead you, and to as many different websites as necessary. But I do think <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000515.html">building a strong online identity is an important strategy for distinguishing yourself</a> in an increasingly online world. So choose carefully, and focus on those things that best represent <i>you</i>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-12-13T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/our-fractured-online-identities/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
