<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Spartan Programming</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/spartan-programming/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
As I grow older and <s>wiser</s>even older as a programmer, I've found that my personal coding style has trended heavily toward minimalism.
</p>
<p>
I was pleased, then, to find many of the coding conventions I've settled on over the last 20 years codified in <a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Spartan_programming">Spartan programming</a>.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="300-movie.jpg" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777051d6970c" height="384" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777051d6970c-pi.jpg" width="512">
</p>
<p>
No, not that sort of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spartan_Army">Spartan</a>, although it is historically related. The particular meaning of <b>spartan</b> I'm referring to is this one:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
(adj) ascetic, ascetical, austere, spartan (practicing great self-denial) <i>"Be systematically ascetic...do...something for no other reason than that you would rather not do it"</i> - William James; <i>"a desert nomad's austere life"; "a spartan diet"; "a spartan existence"</i>
</blockquote>
<p>
I've tried to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000791.html">code smaller</a>, even going so far as to write <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000878.html">no code at all</a> when I can get away with it. <a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Spartan_programming">Spartan programming</a> aligns perfectly with these goals. You strive for <b>simultaneous minimization</b> of your code in many dimensions:
</p>
<ol>
<li>
<a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Horizontal_complexity%2C_spartan_reduction_of">Horizontal complexity</a>. The depth of nesting of control structures.
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Vertical_complexity%2C_spartan_reduction_of">Vertical complexity</a>. The number of lines or length of code.
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Token_count%2C_spartan_reduction_of">Token count</a>.
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Character_count%2C_spartan_reduction_of">Character count</a>.
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Parameters%2C_spartan_reduction_of">Parameters</a>. The number of parameters to a routine or a generic structure.
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Variables%2C_spartan_reduction_of">Variables</a>.
</li>
<li>Looping instructions. The number of iterative instructions and their nesting level.
</li>
<li>Conditionals. The number of <code>if</code> and multiple branch <code>switch</code> statements.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
The discipline of spartan programming means <b>frugal use of variables</b>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Minimize <i>number</i> of variables. Inline variables which are used only once. Take advantage of <code>foreach</code> loops.</li>
<li>Minimize <i>visibility</i> of variables and other identifiers. Define variables at the smallest possible scope.</li>
<li>Minimize <i>accessibility</i> of variables. Prefer the greater encapsulation of <code>private</code> variables.</li>
<li>Minimize <i>variability</i> of variables. Strive to make variables <code>final</code> in Java and <code>const</code> in C++. Use annotations or restrictions whenever possible.</li>
<li>Minimize <i>lifetime</i> of variables. Prefer ephemeral variables to longer lived ones. Avoid persistent variables such as files.</li>
<li>Minimize <i>names</i> of variables. Short-lived, tightly scoped variables can <a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Terse_variable_naming">use concise, terse names</a>.</li>
<li>Minimize <i>use of array</i> variables. Replace them with collections provided by your standard libraries.</li>
</ol>
<p>
It also means <b>frugal use of control structures</b>, with early <code>return</code> whenever possible. This is probably best illustrated with an actual example, starting with raw code and refactoring it using the spartan programming techniques:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Applying Spartan programming techniques <a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/Spartan_programming_C_example">to a C File</a>
</li>
<li>Applying Spartan programming techniques <a href="http://ssdl-wiki.cs.technion.ac.il/wiki/index.php/SendAnEmail_case_study">to a Java function</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
I don't agree with all the rules and guidelines presented here, but I was definitely nodding along with the majority of the page. <b>Minimalism isn't always the right choice, but it's rarely the <i>wrong</i> choice.</b> You could certainly do worse than to adopt the discipline of spartan programming on your next programming project.
</p>
<p>
(hat tip to Yuval Tobias for sending this link my way)
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-07-08T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/spartan-programming/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
