<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Beating CAPTCHAs with .NET code</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/beating-captchas-with-net-code/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I stumbled across an interesting article outlining <a href="http://www.mperfect.net/aiCaptcha/">how to beat the MSDN visual CAPTCHA algorithm with some .NET code</a>. Unfortunately, the author (a Microsoft MVP) demonstrated his "crack" by testing it on the blogs of other MVPs:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote><i>
(if you were one of the 94 people i comment spammed) sorry about that, and hope that you are not pissed. if you are new to my site, then you must realize that i like to stir things up every once in a while. if you've been here before, then i'm hoping you've got a smile on your face, and sort of expect stuff like this from me :) anyways, you were targeted for 2 reasons. 1) because your blog uses CAPTCHA to provide a false sense of security. 2) because we are members of the same group. so i know a handful of you (and know of most of you). could easily have done this against a bunch of strangers ... but did not think that that was a good idea. this is just my way of saying that we've got more work to do. i will not be comment spamming you anymore. unless you comment spam me back in retaliation ... and then i'll have to blast you out of the water ... just kidding.
</i></blockquote>
<p>
So, yeah, the author is kind of a jerk. And he has some problems with capitalization and punctuation, too. He tries to <a href="http://www.mperfect.net/blog/browse.aspx?bid=632428362792968750">explain himself in the FAQ</a>.  Anyway, it's interesting code that appears to leverage the continuous, unbroken lines of contrast between the characters and the background.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-02-15T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/beating-captchas-with-net-code/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
