<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Exploring Vista's Advanced Search</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/exploring-vistas-advanced-search/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I used the file search function in Windows XP a lot, particularly to find groups of files. But the XP search syntax doesn't work in Vista. Vista uses the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/desktopsearch/addresources/advanced.mspx">Windows Desktop Search query syntax</a>. Which means
</p>
<p>
   "*.vbproj;*.csproj"
</p>
<p>
becomes
</p>
<p>
   "ext:(*.vbproj OR *.csproj)"
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Vista's search box in Windows Explorer" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed1a970c" height="385" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed1a970c-pi.png" width="504">
</p>
<p>
Note that the boolean operator <i>must</i> be in all-caps to work. That was painful to figure out.
</p>
<p>
I highly recommend reading through the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/desktopsearch/addresources/advanced.mspx">Windows Desktop Search advanced query reference</a>. First of all, it's completely different than searching in XP, so you'll need to retrain your brain. But it's also a far richer search paradigm than we ever had in XP. And you can <b>use the same CTRL+E search keyboard shortcut</b> that works in your browser to harness its power in Windows Explorer.
</p>
<p>
When you perform a search, note that the Search Tools menu is available; that's our main interface for all the new search options.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="vista-search-tools.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed3f970c" height="110" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed3f970c-pi.png" width="221">
</p>
<p>
From here, you can bring up the Search Pane, which lets you filter your searches to particular file types, and includes an expandable Advanced Search pane.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="vista-search-pane.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed68970c" height="143" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed68970c-pi.png" width="676">
</p>
<p>
As you fill in values in the Advanced Search pane and click Search, the equivalent query terms will be populated in the CTRL+E search box. It's a good way to learn basic search syntax. Once you've learned <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/desktopsearch/addresources/advanced.mspx">the new Vista search syntax</a>, you won't need the Search Pane training wheels any more; you can press CTRL+E and type in what you want. It's Google-icious.
</p>
<p>
There's also an important distinction between indexed search locations and non-indexed search locations. To see the difference, choose "Search Options" from the Search Tools menu.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="vista-folder-search-options.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed88970c" height="479" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fed88970c-pi.png" width="396">
</p>
<p>
Most notably, <b>your search terms will only extend to file contents in indexed locations</b>. I'm also very glad to see search now ignores compressed files by default. This was a real pain in XP, which insisted on digging through 600 megabyte ZIP files as a part of any search.
</p>
<p>
To view indexed locations, or add your own, select Modify Index Locations from the Search Tools menu. On a default Vista install, there are only three indexed locations:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Offline Files
</li>
<li>c:Program DataMicrosoftWindowsStart Menu
</li>
<li>c:Users
</li>
</ul>
<p>
There is one big caveat here: <b>the full-text indexer only indexes file extensions that it understands</b>. To view or modify the list of file extensions the indexer understands, click the Advanced Options button on the Modify Index Locations dialog, then select the File Types tab.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Vista indexes, advanced options button, file types tab" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fedab970c" height="495" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fedab970c-pi.png" width="471">
</p>
<p>
Perhaps the coolest new search feature is that <b>you can enter searches directly from the Windows start menu</b>. Try it. Hit the Windows key and just start typing search queries. There's nothing to install, nothing to configure, searching <i>just works</i> in Vista. It's about time.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-11-22T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/exploring-vistas-advanced-search/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
