<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Total Users Does Not Equal Total Usage</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/total-users-does-not-equal-total-usage/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
As of August 9th, 2006, <a href="http://internet.seekingalpha.com/article/15237">MySpace has 100 million members</a>. For reference, the population of California is approximately 36 million, and the population of the United States is approximately 300 million.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="myspace-usa-population.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fdf50970c" height="184" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/08/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fdf50970c-pi.png" width="290">
<img alt="myspace-california-population.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fdf72970c" height="184" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/08/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fdf72970c-pi.png" width="163">
<img alt="myspace-population.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fdf8e970c" height="184" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/08/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fdf8e970c-pi.png" width="312">
</p>
<p>
I have a hard time believing that <b>1 in 3 Americans could conceivably be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MySpace">MySpace</a> users.</b>
</p>
<p>
I'm not the only person to be skeptical of these inflated "member" numbers. Robert Scoble recently <a href="http://scobleizer.wordpress.com/2006/08/20/is-microsoft-really-the-largest-blog-vendor/">took issue with the claim that Windows Live Spaces is the largest blogging service on the planet</a>. He did <a href="https://scobleizer.wordpress.com/2006/08/20/wheres-the-blog-in-windows-live-spaces">a little ad-hoc investigation of Windows Live Spaces</a>. Most of the member pages he visited were virtual ghost towns.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.25hoursaday.com/weblog/PermaLink.aspx?guid=2b53b317-ef09-449e-b6d9-1d184177c4df">Dare Obasanjo</a> addresses this criticism head-on:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
The number of spaces on Windows Live Spaces isn't a particularly interesting metric to me nor is it to anyone I know who works on the product. <b>We are more interested in the number of people who actually use our service</b> and get value added to their lives by being able to share, discuss and communicate with their friends, families and total strangers.
</blockquote>
<p>
Kudos to Dare for cutting to the heart of this debate. Who cares how many users signed up for your free service? <b>How many users actually <i>use</i> it?</b>
</p>
<p>
To illustrate the absurdity of user counts as a metric, Dare cited the <a href="http://www.livejournal.com/stats.bml">LiveJournal stats page</a>. According to that page, LiveJournal has approximately 11 million accounts. However:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<b>1 in 3</b> accounts are <i>never</i> used.
</li>
<li>
<b>1 in 5</b> accounts are "active in some way".
</li>
<li>
<b>1 in 10</b> accounts updated in the last 30 days.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
If the LiveJournal statistics are representative of other social networking websites, then we should immediately divide the total number of "users", "spaces", or "accounts", by five. Maybe even by ten! That's a realistic estimate of how many people are actually using the service.
</p>
<p>
Total number of LiveJournal accounts:
</p>
<p>
<font size="5">11 million</font>
</p>
<p>
Total number of <i>active</i> LiveJournal accounts:
</p>
<p>
<font size="5">1.5 million</font>
</p>
<p>
And that's still an optimistic estimate, because it doesn't factor in multiple accounts established by the same person.
</p>
<p>
Now if only MySpace and Windows Live Spaces would be as forthcoming about the actual <i>usage</i> of their service, instead of bandying around meaningless user counts.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-08-21T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/total-users-does-not-equal-total-usage/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
