<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>The Great Enterprise Software Swindle</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-great-enterprise-software-swindle/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
After nearly four years working for a Fortune 50 company, I am now completely convinced that <b>the term "Enterprise", as applied to software, is synonymous with "crappy".</b>
</p>
<p>
Clearly I'm not the only guy to notice the <a href="http://www.codebetter.com/blogs/brendan.tompkins/archive/2004/12/17/37523.aspx">apparently linear price to bug ratio</a> in the so-called "Enterprise" software I've been exposed to. It's <a href="http://www.davidgalbraith.org/archives/000561.html">an embarrassment</a>. But it also seems to be a standard part of the business model for these companies. The rampant bugs in their Enterprise Software-- which we already paid millions for-- force us to contract with the "professional services" arm of said company, who then get to work busily <i>fixing the bugs in their own product</i> for $100/hour.
</p>
<p>
Worst of all, if your organization has used this Enterprise Software for a year or two, you've likely customized the heck out of it. The idea of a one-size-fits-all software package-- particularly one of this magnitude-- is laughable. And yet that's one of the illusions that drives sales of these packages in the first place. <b>It's as if the salespeople watched one too many Warner Brothers cartoons, and they're expecting to get another delivery from ACME Corporation any minute now.</b>
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Wile E. Coyote and ACME Corporation" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fae07970c" height="203" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/03/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fae07970c-pi.png" width="326">
</p>
<p>
So, once you factor in natural inertia, plus the customizations required to get the functionality you paid for, the cost of conversion to a competing product is brutal. It's easy to get sweet-talked into yet another version of the devil you know, on the off chance that hey-- maybe this year it might not suck. As much.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000032.html">It's madness</a>. As far as I'm concerned, the word "Enterprise" is now so tainted that it's best used as an epithet. <i>Dude, your software sucks so much, it's enterprise software.</i>
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-03-02T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-great-enterprise-software-swindle/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
