<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>In praise of Beyond Compare</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/in-praise-of-beyond-compare/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
It's a shame that <a href="http://www.scootersoftware.com/home.php">Beyond Compare</a> isn't listed in more <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/ScottHanselmans2005UltimateDeveloperAndPowerUsersToolList.aspx">"favorite tool" lists</a>. This amazing little folder and file differencing tool has earned its spot in my core toolset a dozen times over. Here's a screenshot of it in action:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Screenshot of Beyond Compare in action" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d5f5e970b" height="634" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d5f5e970b-pi.png" width="807">
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000153.html">I've mentioned Beyond Compare before</a>, but even a year later, few developers seem to know about it. If you haven't tried it yet, what are you waiting for? Are you <a href="http://www.codeproject.com/csharp/DiffEngine.asp">writing your own diff program in c#</a>? <a href="http://www.scootersoftware.com/beycomp.exe">Give it a 30-day trial spin</a>, and check out <a href="http://www.scootersoftware.com/download.php?c=v2plugins">the viewer plugins</a>, too.
</p>
<p>
Here are a few beginner tips when using Beyond Compare:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Make use of the ultra-handy right-click explorer file and folder context menus to compare stuff.
</li>
<li>The default comparison is file size plus date and time, which is super speedy but not always accurate. Use the little scales icon (or the Session | Comparison Control menu) to switch the comparison type to Size and CRC.
</li>
<li>When viewing a file comparison, use the referee icon (or the Tools | Edit Current Rules menu) to tweak the file comparison rules. I usually turn off all the options under "Unimportant Text" such as leading whitespace, case, line endings, etcetera.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-11-29T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/in-praise-of-beyond-compare/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
