<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Server Fault: Calling All Lusers</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/server-fault-calling-all-lusers/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
It's pop quiz time! Put away your notes, and let's begin.
</p>
<p>
a) Do you own this book?*
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0130206016/?tag=codihorr-20"><img alt="unix-system-administration-handbook.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b01287770997b970c" height="542" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2009/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b01287770997b970c-pi.png" width="396"></a>
</p>
<p>
b) Do you know who this man is?
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://blogs.technet.com/markrussinovich/"><img alt="mark-russinovich-sysinternals.jpg" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777099a0970c" height="384" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2009/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777099a0970c-pi.jpg" width="405"></a>
</p>
<p>
c) Does this FAQ look <a href="http://www.faqs.org/faqs/sysadmin-recovery/">familiar</a> to you?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
3) OUR LITTLE FRIEND, THE COMPUTER<br>
3.1) Are there any OSes that don't suck?<br>
3.2) Are there any vendors that don't suck?<br>
3.3) How about any hardware?<br>
3.4) Just HOW MUCH does this system suck?<br>
3.5) Where can I find clueful tech support?<br>
3.6) What can I do to help my computers behave?<br>
</blockquote>
<p>
d) Does the acronym <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bastard_Operator_From_Hell">BOFH</a> mean anything to you?
</p>
<p>
e) Do you think <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/1573980420/?tag=codihorr-20">this</a> is funny?
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/1573980420/?tag=codihorr-20"><img alt="april-fools-day-rfcs.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777099cd970c" height="496" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2009/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777099cd970c-pi.png" width="371"></a>
</p>
<p>
If you answered "yes" to any of the above, I am sorry to inform you that <b>you may be a system administrator or IT professional</b>. But I do have one bit of potentially, at least <i>theoretically</i> good news for you:
</p>
<p>
<b><a href="http://serverfault.com">Server Fault</a> is now in public beta!</b>
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://serverfault.com"><img alt="serverfault-logo.png" border="0" height="48" src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/serverfault-logo.png" width="250"></a>
</p>
<p>
Server Fault is a sister site to Stack Overflow, which <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001169.html">we launched back in September 2008</a>. It uses the same engine, but it's <a href="http://serverfault.com/faq">not just for programmers</a> any more:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
Server Fault is for <b>system administrators and IT professionals</b>, people who manage or maintain computers in a professional capacity. If you are in charge of ...
<ul>
<li>servers
</li>
<li>networks
</li>
<li>many desktop PCs (other than your own)
</li>
</ul>
... then you're in the right place to ask your question! Well, as long as the question is about your servers, your networks, or desktops you support, anyway.
<p>
Please note that Server Fault is <b>not for general computer troubleshooting questions</b>; if you paid for that desktop hardware, and it's your personal workstation, it is unlikely that your question is appropriate for Server Fault.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
I occasionally dabble in system administration and IT professional stuff; <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001233.html">my last blog entry was about RAID</a>, for example. As a programmer who <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000874.html">loves hardware</a> as much as software, I've wanted this site for months, and I'm thrilled to see it go live, as I <a href="http://runasradio.com/default.aspx?showNum=109">explained on a recent RunAs radio podcast</a>.
</p>
<p>
Although there is certainly some crossover, we believe that the programming community and the IT/sysadmin community are different beasts. Just because you're a hotshot programmer doesn't mean you have mastered networking and server configuration. And I've met a few sysadmins who could script circles around my code. That's why <a href="http://serverfault.com">Server Fault</a> gets its own domain, user profiles, and reputation system.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.userfriendly.org/cartoons/archives/99aug/19990815.html"><img alt="userfriendly-evolution-of-language.png" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877709a04970c" height="441" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2009/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877709a04970c-pi.png" width="639"></a>
</p>
<p>
<b>So if you're a bona-fide BOFH, or just a wanna-be BOFH <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luser">luser</a> like me, <a href="http://serverfault.com">join us on Server Fault</a></b>. Who knows, maybe we lusers can learn something from each other.
</p>
<p>
<small>* (For the record, yes, I do own that book -- although I am easily the world's <i>worst</i> UNIX system administrator.)</small>
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2009-05-28T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/server-fault-calling-all-lusers/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
