<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>VS.NET and Code Regions</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/vsnet-and-code-regions/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I'm currently working on a project where almost every function has its own region. At first I found this convention onerous, but as I used it, I saw why it was necessary. <b>The default Visual Studio .NET outlining support leaves a lot to be desired.</b> Take your typical commented Page_Load method:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<pre language="c#">
/// &lt;summary&gt;
/// This method is called when the Page's Load event has been fired.
/// &lt;/summary&gt;
/// &lt;param name="sender"&gt;The &lt;see cref="object"/&gt; that fired the event.&lt;/param&gt;
/// &lt;param name="e"&gt;The &lt;see cref="EventArgs"/&gt; of the event.&lt;/param&gt;
private void Page_Load(object sender, System.EventArgs e)
{
if (!Page.IsPostBack)
{
// do stuff
}
}
</pre>
<p>
That function will outline in two blocks: one for the XML comments, and another for the actual code itself:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Page_Load method using default outlining" border="0" height="30" src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/page_load_outlined.gif" width="490">
</p>
<p>
It's aggravating that there is no built in support for <b>outlining the entire function and the comments.</b> Hence, the need for a simple region around the comments and the function, which provides the outlining support you might expect in the first place:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Page_Load method using custom region" border="0" height="19" src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/page_load_regioned.gif" width="471">
</p>
<p>
I just checked, and VS.NET 2005 (aka Whidbey) has this same bad behavior. What a bummer. I am working on a macro that Region-izes all the functions in a file, but in the meantime you might want to check out the <a href="http://www.codeproject.com/csharp/DocumentatorMacros.asp">Documentator macros on CodeProject</a>. They combine commenting and regionizing into one function, which isn't always what I want, but it's close enough to start.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-07-04T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/vsnet-and-code-regions/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
