<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Using the Command Window</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/using-the-command-window/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
One of the most underappreciated features of Visual Studio .NET 2003 is the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/en-us/vsintro7/html/vxurfTheCommandLineWindow.asp">Command Window</a>. Did you know there are a bunch of <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/vsintro7/html/vxgrfPredefinedCommandLineAliases.asp">command alias shortcuts</a> available for use in the command window? I use '?' all the time, but I didn't know about the others. And then there's the subtle distinction between <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/vsintro7/html/vxurfImmediateModeCommandWindow.asp">immediate mode</a> and <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/vsintro7/html/vxurfCommandModeCommandWindow.asp">command mode</a>: enter <b>&gt;cmd</b> and <b>immed</b> to switch between the two.
</p>
<p>
As I mentioned above, I frequently use <b>?(value)</b> to dump out the contents of structures in the Command Window. This works, but it's kinda ghetto. A more sophisticated way to view data structures in real time will appear in Whidbey; <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/scottno/archive/2004/04/17/115328.aspx">custom data visualizers</a>, which automatically display structures in an easier to understand visual format. And naturally you can extend the visualizers with custom viewers for whatever crazy data structure you're creating, too-- <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/04/05/VisualStudio2005Debugging/">even  the humble hashtable</a>.
</p>
<p>
You don't have to wait for Whidbey, though. There are a handful of less integrated, but still useful, ad-hoc visualizers available for VS.NET 2003. For example, <a href="http://www.codeproject.com/csharp/DSWatch.asp">this DataSet visualizer</a>, and Daniel Cazzulino offers this <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/cazzu/archive/2004/02/10/70658.aspx">cool visualization hack using VSTweak</a>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2004-09-05T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/using-the-command-window/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
