<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>How Not to Give a Presentation</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-not-to-give-a-presentation/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I hold speakers to relatively high standards. They get paid to present to large groups because they're ostensibly good communicators. And I cannot believe the beginner mistakes some of the speakers are making here at VSLive.
</p>
<p>
Based on my experiences over the last two days, here are a few sure-fire ways <i>not</i> to give a presentation:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>
<b>Begin by establishing how impressive you are.</b> Make sure we know all about your accomplishments and any books you've written. Be sure to plug your company and/or website. After all, this presentation is <a href="http://headrush.typepad.com/creating_passionate_users/2005/01/users_shouldnt_.html">about you</a>.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Present a detailed presentation agenda</b>. Before you can get to any content at all, you must dutifully itemize the <i>table of contents!</i> You know how people love reading the table of contents. It builds suspense. It's exciting. It keeps the audience on the edges of their seats, wondering "when will I actually see any content in this presentation"?
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Every slide should be absolutely jam-packed with information.</b> Use as many bullet points and words on your slides as possible.  Feel free to slap a few helpful URLs in there, too. If you can't fit it all on one slide, try a smaller font.
<p>
<img alt="Sample slide, blurred to protect the guilty" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fcce8970c" height="392" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/01/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fcce8970c-pi.png" width="520">
</p>
<p>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Explain everything with bullet points.</b> Don't show the audience. <a href="http://headrush.typepad.com/creating_passionate_users/2005/06/kill_your_prese.html">Tell them</a>. Avoid pictures or, even worse, actual demonstrations. Feel free to use several slides to properly explain things.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Read every word on your slides.</b> Audiences can't read. It's your responsibility to do all the reading for them. But don't waste their time with a bunch of elaboration. Be succinct. Say exactly what is on each slide, then move on to the next slide.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>If you make a mistake or something goes wrong, take a few minutes to fix it.</b> The audience can wait. While you're fixing things up, try that NASCAR joke again. It's hilarious.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Use the highest possible desktop resolution.</b> Show off your laptop's new widescreen LCD. Besides, limited resolutions and large fonts are <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000503.html">childish and unprofessional</a>.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Summarize everything at the end.</b> Audiences are notoriously forgetful. Spend the last few minutes patiently recapping everything they just saw.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>If you run out of time at the end of your session, keep going.</b> The audience paid good money to see your presentation, so make sure they see it all. Your time is important.
<p></p>
</li>
<li>
<b>Don't take any questions.</b> The content and quality of your presentation speaks for itself.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
This stuff would be funny if it wasn't happening every single day. <a href="http://blogs.technet.com/jesper_johansson/archive/2005/08/24/Death_by_PowerPoint.aspx">Death by PowerPoint</a>, indeed.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-01-31T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-not-to-give-a-presentation/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
