<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Revenge of Notepad</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/revenge-of-notepad/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><br>
<a href="http://www.notepad.org/">I use notepad.exe dozens of times a day</a>. Given the severely limited functionality of Notepad, it's incredible that it has taken me this long to find a suitable replacement for what is, evidently, a <b>core part of my developer toolkit</b>. Check out <a href="http://www.flos-freeware.ch/notepad2.html">Notepad2</a>:
<blockquote><i>The original Notepad shipped with Windows is probably the handiest program of all times, small, fast, without frills! Notepad2 tries to follow this principle, it's a small, fast and free text editor with syntax highlighting for HTML and other common languages.</i></blockquote>
Amen, brother! And don't worry, it's still relatively small at 550kb. But <b>look at everything you get for that additional 450kb:</b>
<ul>
<li>Customizable syntax highlighting engine (HTML, XML, CSS, JavaScript, VBScript, ASP, PHP, CSS, Perl/CGI, C/C++, C#, Java, VB, Pascal, Assembler, SQL, Python, NSIS, INI, REG, INF, BAT, DIFF)
</li>
<li>Drag &amp; drop text editing inside and outside Notepad2
</li>
<li>Basic regular expression search and replace
</li>
<li>Useful word, line and block editing shortcuts
</li>
<li>Rectangular selection (Alt+Mouse)
</li>
<li>Brace matching, auto indent, long line marker, zoom functions
</li>
<li>Support for Unicode, UTF-8, Unix and Mac text files
</li>
<li>Open shell links
</li>
<li>Mostly adjustable</li>
</ul>
Still not convinced? Here's a screenshot of me viewing some Perl scripts that come with the <a href="http://www.tivo.com/developer/">Tivo Home Media Option developer kit</a>:<br>
<br>
<img src="http://www.codinghorror.com/files/notepad2/screenshot_notepad2.gif">
<br>
<br>
I recommend <b>overwriting the original notepad.exe</b> with this version, for simplicity's sake. You'll get some complaints from the XP file protection mechanism, but it works. And it kicks ass! I should have done this two years ago.<br>
<br>
I downloaded the VC++ source and compiled the latest version with every optimization I could locate in the project properties dialog (Hey, I don't get to work with C++ much). You can download a <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/files/notepad2/notepad2.zip">zipped version of my compiled notepad2.exe</a> (~250kb), or if you prefer, get it from <a href="http://www.flos-freeware.ch/notepad2.html">the official website</a>.
<br>
<br>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2004-06-12T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/revenge-of-notepad/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
