<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Linus Torvalds, Visual Basic Fan</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/linus-torvalds-visual-basic-fan/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Stiff recently asked a few programmers a <a href="http://www.dodgycoder.net/2012/09/q-with-nine-great-programmers.html">series of open-ended questions</a>:
</p>
<ul>
<li>How did you learn programming? Were schools of any use?
</li>
<li>What's the most important skill every programmer should have?
</li>
<li>Are math and physics important skills for a programmer?
</li>
<li>What will be the next big thing in computer programming?
</li>
<li>If you had three months to learn one relatively new technology, which one would you choose?
</li>
<li>What are your favorite tools and why?
</li>
<li>What's your favorite programming book?
</li>
<li>What's your favorite non-programming book?
</li>
<li>What music do you listen to?
</li>
</ul>
<p>
The participants are all quite notable:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Linus Torvalds (Linux)
</li>
<li>Dave Thomas (Pragmatic Programmer)
</li>
<li>David Heinemeier Hansson (Ruby/Rails)
</li>
<li>Steve Yegge (Google/Amazon)
</li>
<li>Peter Norvig (Google Research Director)
</li>
<li>Guido Van Rossum (Python)
</li>
<li>James Gosling (Java)
</li>
<li>Tim Bray (XML)
</li>
</ul>
<p>
The interesting thing about open-ended questions is that <strong>the answers often reveal more about the person answering the question than they do about the question.</strong> Guido Van Rossum, for example, comes across as kind of a jerk. But the questions generally provoked some <a href="http://www.dodgycoder.net/2012/09/q-with-nine-great-programmers.html">very thoughtful responses</a>.
</p>
<p>
The most surprising response, however, was from Linus Torvalds. When asked what the "next big thing" would be in computer programming, here's part of his reply:
</p>
<blockquote>
For example, <strong>I personally believe that Visual Basic did more for programming than Object-Oriented Languages did.</strong> Yet people laugh at VB and say it's a bad language, and they've been talking about OO languages for decades.
<p>
And no, Visual Basic wasn't a great language, but I think the easy database interfaces in VB were fundamentally more important than object orientation is, for example.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Evidently we have another inductee into the <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000087.html">he-man object hater's club</a>.
</p>
<p>
Maybe the moral of this story is that we should value practical aspects of a language far more heavily than relatively meaningless technical merits. Or maybe I just get a kick out of hearing <strong>Linus Torvalds, the king of hard-core C geeks, compliment Visual Basic</strong>.
</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-07-31T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/linus-torvalds-visual-basic-fan/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
