<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>This Site May Harm Your Computer</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/this-site-may-harm-your-computer/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
<a href="http://www.usenix.org/events/hotbots07/tech/full_papers/provos/provos.pdf">The Ghost In The Browser: Analysis of Web-based Malware</a> (pdf) describes <b>how Google is leveraging their overwhelming search dominance to combat browser malware installations</b>. In <a href="http://www.mattcutts.com/blog/siteadvisor-study/">a blog entry last summer</a>, Matt Cutts said:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
Given how much I hate web pages that install malicious software or abuse browser security holes, I'd like it if we did even more to protect our users.
</blockquote>
<p>
Apparently, they've <a href="http://www.mattcutts.com/blog/how-google-handles-malware-a-historical-overview/">done even more to protect users</a> since then. Here's a Google search result tagged with the ominous warning "This site may harm your computer":
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Search results page with an entry tagged 'this site may harm your computer'" border="1" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7e77970b" height="204" hspace="4" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7e77970b-pi.png" style="border-color:#ccc;" vspace="4" width="616">
</p>
<p>
Clicking <a href="http://www.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=45449&amp;topic=360&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=malwarewarninglink&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=help">"This site may harm your computer"</a> leads to a Google support page. Attempting to click through to the actual website results in an interstitial warning, offering no way to click through:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Warning - vsiting this site may harm your computer!" border="1" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7e88970b" height="352" hspace="4" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7e88970b-pi.png" style="border-color:#ccc;" vspace="4/" width="669">
</p>
<p>
I think this is a fairly effective method of warning away most rational users from a clearly evil website. Of course, users who desire whatever media, software, or pornography the site is hawking can still type the URL in their address bar. Users will <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000347.html">find a way to see the dancing bunnies</a> if they really, <i>really</i> want to, no matter how many warnings and barriers you blast in front of them.
</p>
<p>
If you want to see what's behind that URL, fair warning: in addition to being outright dangerous for a machine that's not patched to the gills, it's NSFW in a big way. A little investigation showed that it's doing the following:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Attempts to use the remote data services ActiveX control.
</li>
<li>Shows a spoof HTML page with the text "windows media player cannot play video file; Click here to download missing Video ActiveX object". The download runs setup.exe.
</li>
<li>Runs Javascript with exploit sniffing code.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
If you accept that Google wields the immense power of being <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000767.html">the de-facto start page for the internet</a>, then maybe this kind of policing effort comes with the territory. <b>To do nothing-- to let these purely evil sites show up in Google results with no warning whatsoever-- would be irresponsible.</b> Although a person might be performing questionable searches to get this page in their results, it's irrelevant. Despite the individual ethics of the person using that one computer, a compromised computer will be used for attacks and spam against everyone.
</p>
<p>
Still, I'm a little curious. Why does Google <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000767.html">deploy the ultimate weapon of search delisting</a> on sites using black-hat SEO techniques to game search rankings, while known evil malware sites get stern warning interstitials instead? I brought up the Google result by doing a direct search on the domain name. The very same search <b>produces no results on live.com or ask.com</b>. Clearly that site has been delisted by everyone except Google. The domain still has a PageRank of four. I applaud the effort, but what value does keeping a site like that in your search index have for users?
</p>
<p>
Even if your web site is <i>not</i> evil, it's possible for others to inject malicious code into your page if you're not careful. The <a href="http://www.usenix.org/events/hotbots07/tech/full_papers/provos/provos.pdf">Google whitepaper</a> provides three external vectors that can turn a good web page to the dark side:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Compromised webservers can insert malicious code into all HTML pages served
</li>
<li>Pages which allow user-contributed HTML, where the HTML hasn't been properly sanitized
</li>
<li>The use of questionable advertising content, or compromised ad servers
</li>
</ul>
<p>
It's scary how many ways this can happen. I strongly urge you to <a href="http://www.usenix.org/events/hotbots07/tech/full_papers/provos/provos.pdf">read the whitepaper</a> to get all the gory details.
</p>
<p>
Google's paper says <b>one in ten webpages contains malicious code</b>. The most direct way to address malware delivered via web pages is to increase the security of the operating system and the browser, so "drive-by downloads" cannot happen without the user's explicit consent. But a problem as large as malware should be attacked on multiple fronts. Search engines are in a unique position to help index and identify malicious webpages, and prevent them from being accessible in search results. It's encouraging to read about Google's architecture for automatically identifying malicious URLs. I don't think it's fair to call this <a href="http://www.roughtype.com/archives/2007/05/driveby_malware.php">Google policing the web</a>; it's just good, ethical business to <b>filter out the evil</b>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-05-10T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/this-site-may-harm-your-computer/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
