<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>What's Wrong With Setup.exe?</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/whats-wrong-with-setupexe/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Ned Batchelder shares a <a href="http://www.nedbatchelder.com/blog/200706.html#e20070623T082532">complaint about the Mac application installation process</a>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
Here's what I did to install the application Foo [on the Mac]:
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Downloaded FooDownload.dmg.zip to the desktop.
</li>
<li>StuffIt Expander launched automatically, and gave me a FooDownload.dmg Folder on the desktop.
</li>
<li>At this point, nothing is happening, so I opened the folder, inside was a FooDownload.dmg icon.
</li>
<li>I opened that, a license agreement appears.
</li>
<li>I agreed to that, and a window appears with an application icon, and instructions to "Drag this icon to your Applications folder".
</li>
<li>I have to find the Applications folder, and drop the icon into it.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
At this point, the application is installed. To clean up, I had to:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Close the Applications folder.
</li>
<li>Close the window with the dragging instructions.
</li>
<li>Close the FooDownload.dmg Folder window.
</li>
<li>Get rid of the three (!) things on the desktop: The dmg, the FooDownload.dmg Folder, and the FooDownload.dmg.zip file.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
To me, that seems like a lot of manual steps. In the Windows world, you'll sometimes find shareware where the author gives two options: an installer, or a zip file where you can do everything yourself. The Mac installation process is like the Windows do-it-all-yourself case.
</p>
<p>
Again, I'm not trying to slam the Mac. I genuinely do not understand why on a platform that makes things really simple, where the mantra is that stuff "just works", ordinary users are expected to do all these manual steps.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
I've often wondered the same thing-- <b>why does the Mac require the user to jump through a bunch of manual hoops to install an application?</b> Why not use a traditional installer (a.k.a. setup.exe) that automates this manual work for you?
</p>
<p>
To be fair, Windows applications aren't always delivered with installers, either. One of the apps I use is Kenny Kerr's excellent <a href="http://www.windowclippings.com/">Window Clippings</a>. It's delivered as a single executable in a compressed ZIP file. It's a pleasingly simple arrangement, but it's also more work me, the user. Consider how I "install" Windows Clippings:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Manual program installation screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9c1d970b" height="247" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9c1d970b-pi.png" width="419">
</p>
<p>
I have to:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Extract the executable from the ZIP file.
</li>
<li>Create a WindowsClippings folder in the C:Program Files folder
</li>
<li>Move the WindowsClippings.exe file to the new folder I just created
</li>
<li>Create a start menu shortcut for WindowsClippings
</li>
</ol>
<p>
That's a lot of tedious, error-prone steps I have to perform before I can run the application. And no two users will have Windows Clippings installed the same way. Some may opt to run it from their desktop, or a temporary folder, or some other inappropriate location. Is this really what we want to subject our users to?
</p>
<p>
Even as a power user, I find this level of control not only unnecessary but onerous. That's why it's so strange to me that the "normal" Mac install parallels the sophisticated "power user" Windows install. A typical user doesn't want this level of control, and they certainly <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000461.html">don't want to learn about disks and folders</a>. They just want the application to work. <b>Wouldn't a big giant button that says "Install Me" be a better experience for the user?</b>
</p>
<p>
Traditional Windows installers may be easier than a Mac-style manual install, but they aren't exactly model citizens either. Most installers ask users dozens of questions across multiple wizard pages, along with the <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000892.html">inevitable end user license agreement</a> you get strongarmed into accepting.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Setup program installation screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9c33970b" height="400" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9c33970b-pi.png" width="592">
</p>
<p>
The WinAmp installer is fairly typical. It's five pages long, and asks me to decide the following:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Do you accept our <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EULA">EULA</a>?
</li>
<li>What program options do I want installed? Visualization? Extra Audio Output? User Interface Extensions?
</li>
<li>What icons do I want installed? Start menu? Desktop? Quicklaunch? System Tray?
</li>
<li>Do I want to associate WinAmp with audio files? With CDs? With playlists?
</li>
<li>Where do I want WinAmp installed; at what path?
</li>
<li>Do I want shared settings for all users or individual settings?
</li>
<li>What are my internet connection settings? Do I have a proxy? Do I want to download needed codecs?
</li>
</ul>
<p>
That's <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000377.html">a whole lot of thinking</a> necessary to install a tiny little music player. And that's the <i>minimal</i> install-- the lite version that the WinAmp site does its best to <a href="http://www.winamp.com/player/features">hide</a> from me!
</p>
<p>
Perhaps a better approach is the "No-Questions-Asked" installation featured in <a href="http://www.just-great-software.com/">JGSoft applications</a>.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Setup, no questions asked installation" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9c4c970b" height="327" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9c4c970b-pi.png" width="517">
</p>
<p>
If only more applications-- Mac or Windows-- made it this easy on the user. That's about as close as we can get today to the big giant "Install Me" button I think most users are looking for.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-07-18T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/whats-wrong-with-setupexe/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
