<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Folding: The Death of the General Purpose CPU</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/folding-the-death-of-the-general-purpose-cpu/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
A few recent articles have highlighted the <a href="http://gizmodo.com/gadgets/home-entertainment/breaking-ps3-folding-ps3-triples-folding-at-homes-computing-power-to-over-500-tflopspflops-in-spitting-range-246664.php">disproportionate contribution</a> Playstation 3 consoles are making to the <a href="http://fah-web.stanford.edu">Folding@Home</a> effort. The <a href="http://fah-web.stanford.edu/cgi-bin/main.py?qtype=osstats">OS statistics page for Folding@Home</a> tells the tale:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<table width="450">
<tr>
<td> </td>
<td align="right"><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLOPS">TFLOPS</a></td>
<td align="right">Active CPUs</td>
<td align="right">Total CPUs
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Windows</td>
<td align="right">152</td>
<td align="right">160,173</td>
<td align="right">1,626,609
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac/PPC</td>
<td align="right">7</td>
<td align="right">8,776</td>
<td align="right">95,435
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac/Intel</td>
<td align="right">9</td>
<td align="right">2,864</td>
<td align="right">7,400
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Linux</td>
<td align="right">43</td>
<td align="right">25,239</td>
<td align="right">216,067
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GPU</td>
<td align="right">43</td>
<td align="right">733</td>
<td align="right">2,228
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PS3</td>
<td align="right"><font color="red">659</font></td>
<td align="right">26,911</td>
<td align="right">29,843
</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
There are a couple caveats to bear in mind when reading this chart:
</p>
<ol>
<li>The measurement of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLOPS">FLOPS</a> isn't an exact science. It would be more accurate to compare actual work units returned, but I don't see any way to do that from the folding statistics page.
</li>
<li>Current PC and Mac / PPC contributors span the entire gamut of CPUs released in the last seven years.
</li>
<li>Folding does cost money, in the form of electricity. Superior clients offer efficiency: bang per watt. You could make a compelling argument that certain clients with low efficiency aren't worth the cost of the electricity they're using. For reference, a <a href="http://www.hardcoreware.net/reviews/review-356-2.htm">PS3</a> and <a href="http://techreport.com/reviews/2006q3/core2/index.x?pg=16">a gaming-class PC</a> both use about 200 watts of power under load.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
The Playstation 3 is indeed dominating the charts; as of this writing, the PS3 is responsible for a whopping 72 percent of the computing power in the entire Folding@Home project.
</p>
<p>
<font color="red">UPDATE: as of 3/26/2007, the F@H network has arbitrarily halved the TFLOPS score for the PS3.</font>
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://folding.stanford.edu/FAQ-PS3.html"><img alt="PS3 folding user interface" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7eb8970b" height="426" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/03/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7eb8970b-pi.jpg" width="580"></a>
</p>
<p>
<b>It's only a matter of time-- a few weeks at most-- before the PS3 constitutes more than 95 percent of the computing power in the entire Folding@Home network.</b> This doesn't surprise me in the least. The Playstation 3 can harness the considerable power of its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cell_microprocessor">specialized Cell CPU</a> to crunch work units far more efficiently than any general purpose CPU ever could.
</p>
<p>
If you look closely at the chart, you'll see even more powerful evidence of the dominance of specialized processors.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="TFLOPS per CPU type graph" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7ec8970b" height="434" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/03/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d7ec8970b-pi.png" width="639">
</p>
<p>
GPU clients run on modern, high-end video cards. <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000732.html">The GPU on these video cards is even more specialized</a> than the Cell processor in the PS3.
</p>
<p>
The GPU client is limited to the current high-end ATI X1800 and X1900 video cards at the moment, which are already a generation behind NVIDIA's newest 8800 series. Even so, <b>the GPU clients are almost 2.5 times faster than the PS3</b>. Of course, this performance differential is more than balanced by the fact that PS3 is an easily obtainible (albeit somewhat expensive) consumer item; it's trivially easy to add one to the Folding@Home network, whereas the Folding@Home GPU client is quite immature, and few users have the necessary high-end ATI video cards to use it.
</p>
<p>
But the <i>real</i> lesson of this chart lies in the OS X / Intel data point. Intel-based Macs are, by definition, based on only the newest Intel processors-- Core Duo or better. Even so, it's an utter blowout:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<table width="300">
<tr>
<td>Intel Core Duo</td>
<td>1x
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PS3</td>
<td>
<font color="red">7.8x faster</font>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GPU</td>
<td>
<font color="red">18.6x faster</font>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
With these kinds of performance ratios-- and I expect the performance gap to <i>widen</i> every year-- <b>there's almost no point in adding general purpose CPUs to the folding network any more.</b> It's a waste of time, effort, and electricity.
</p>
<p>
For folding and other distributed computing efforts, it's <b>the death of the general purpose CPU as we know it</b>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-03-23T13:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/folding-the-death-of-the-general-purpose-cpu/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
