<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Fear of Writing</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/fear-of-writing/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>When I meet people that <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000297.html">have something to say, and an interesting way of saying it</a>, I encourage them to blog. But there's one big hurdle many people simply never get past: the actual writing.</p>
<p>
I can respect that. <strong>Writing is hard.</strong> People spend their entire lives learning how to write effectively. It isn't something you can fake. It isn't something you can buy. You have to work at it.</p>
<p>That's exactly why people who are afraid they can't write <em>should</em> be blogging. It's exercise. No matter how out of shape you are, if you exercise a few times a week, you'll inevitably get fitter. <strong>Write a small blog entry a few times every week and you're bound to become a better writer.</strong> If you're not writing because you're intimidated by writing, well, you're likely to stay that way forever.</p>
<p>If you're still hesitant, I highly recommend John Scalzi's <a href="http://www.scalzi.com/whatever/004023.html">Writing Tips for Non-Writers Who Don't Want to Work at Writing</a>, and Brian Marick's <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20050403185924/http://www.testing.com/cgi-bin/blog/2004/11/16">Hints for Revising</a>. They're absolutely dead on with every point. <strong>Consider your writing a natural extension of your spoken conversations</strong>. If you aren't comfortable reading it out loud, rewrite it until you are. In the words of <a href="http://www.elmoreleonard.com/index.php?/forums/viewthread/20">Elmore Leonard</a>:</p>
<blockquote>If it sounds like writing, I rewrite it.</blockquote>
<p>Blogging isn't for everyone. But if you think it might be for you, <strong>don't let fear of writing keep you from doing it</strong>.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-02-14T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/fear-of-writing/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
