<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>MAME Cocktail Arcade</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/mame-cocktail-arcade/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
After years of resistance, I finally buckled. I ordered a <a href="http://www.dreamarcades.com/kits/3s.shtml">3-way MAME cocktail arcade kit</a>:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="3-way MAME cocktail kit" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbce2970c" height="252" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/01/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbce2970c-pi.jpg" width="265">
</p>
<p>
Over the last few years, the homebrew arcade market has spawned a number of businesses specializing in prefab cabinets-- think IKEA meets <a href="http://www.mame.net">MAME</a>. They ship you the cabinet in a large box, and you assemble it with a screwdriver and install standard PC monitors and components inside.
</p>
<p>
Most people choose <b>full-size upright cabinets</b>, such as <a href="http://www.retroblast.com/reviews/slikcab_1.html">this SlikStik kit</a>, a familiar arcade format. They also sell <a href="http://www.slikstik.com/SearchResult.aspx?CategoryID=3">the controllers seperately</a>, which come in a staggering array of 1, 2, and even 4 player versions with dual joysticks, trackballs, and spinners:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="SlikStik Arcade Cabinet in play" height="300" src="http://www.retroblast.com/photos/cabs/MF2%20cabinet/finished.jpg" width="400">
</p>
<p>
Cocktail cabinets are more space effective, but have some peculiarities. The classic cabinet is head-to-head, so it can only play games in vertical orientation. The screen "flips" for each player's turn. That's a serious limitation, since many arcade games are designed to be played horizontally. The kit I ordered is the best of both worlds, with controls for both vertical (head to head) and horizontal games (side by side). There are comprehensive reviews of <a href="http://www.retroblast.com/reviews/dreamarcadesSBS.html">the side-by-side cabinet</a> and <a href="http://www.retroblast.com/reviews/dreamarcades.html">the head-to-head cabinet</a> at RetroBlast. If I had the space, I'd choose a traditional upright arcade cabinet. In the meantime, the cocktail is a better choice for me; it takes up less space, can roll on casters, and, if necessary, can be covered with a tablecloth.
</p>
<p>
I'm looking forward to the kit arriving. I do have a few minor modifications planned, such as <a href="http://www.oscarcontrols.com/speaker/index.shtml">mounting speakers</a> on the outside of the cabinet, installing a real <a href="http://www.arcadeparadise.org/arcade/ap2/coindoor.html">arcade coin door</a> on the side, and some <a href="http://www.retroblast.com/reviews/superbright.html">LED lighting</a>. You're never too old to finally realize that childhood dream: to be the kid who owns his own arcade game!
</p>
<p>
* Hmm, how about a MAME <a href="http://www.eamontales.com/coffeetable/">coffee table</a> project?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-01-09T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/mame-cocktail-arcade/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
