<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>XP Automatic Update Nagging</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/xp-automatic-update-nagging/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Windows XP's automatic update facility is clearly a good thing. Except when an update is installed that requires a reboot and you're working on the computer at the time. Then you get this lovely dialog:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Updating your computer is almost complete. You must restart your computer for the updates to take effect. Do you want to restart your computer now?" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbe59970c" height="132" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbe59970c-pi.png" width="428">
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000019.html">As if I needed another reason to hate dialog boxes.</a> This is perhaps the Naggiest. Dialog. Box. <i>Ever</i>. It can't be dismissed. You get two choices-- Restart Now, or Restart Later. <b>If you click Restart Later, it pops up again ten minutes later, like clockwork.</b> It belongs to wuauclt.exe, part of the Microsoft automatic update provider. I tried killing wuauclt.exe, and like a bad zombie movie, it keeps coming back.
</p>
<p>
I want automatic updates, but I also want to restart my computer when I feel like it. <b>Is there any way to turn off this incredibly annoying nag dialog?</b> <span style="color:red">UPDATE:</span> Thanks to the many commenters, we now have at least two ways to disable Mister Naggy McNaggerson:
</p>
<p>
<b>1. Stop the "Automatic Updates" service.</b>
</p>
<blockquote>
Navigate to Control Panel | Administrative Tools | Services:
<p>
<img alt="Automatic Updates service screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbe6f970c" height="209" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbe6f970c-pi.png" width="693">
</p>
<p>
Right click the Automatic Updates service and stop it. You can also do the same thing at the command line by typing:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<pre>
net stop wuauserv
</pre>
<p>
or you can type this, which does the same thing, and is a little easier to remember:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<pre>
net stop "automatic updates"
</pre>
<p>
After the service is stopped, the nag message stops, too. Then you can reboot when you have time. The service will restart when you reboot.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
<b>2. Modify Group Policy settings.</b>
</p>
<blockquote>
Start, Run "gpedit.msc" to bring up the group policy editor. Then navigate to the folder
<p>
</p>
<pre>
Local Computer Policy
Computer Configuration
Administrative Templates
Windows Components
Windows Update
</pre>
<p>
<img alt="Windows Update group policies screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbe89970c" height="456" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fbe89970c-pi.png" width="777">
</p>
<p>
There are two settings and both will work, so it's your choice. Either enable <b>No auto-restart for schedule Automatic Updates installations</b> or set <b>Re-prompt for restart with scheduled installations</b> to a long time interval, like 1440 minutes.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-05-13T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/xp-automatic-update-nagging/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
