<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>FizzBuzz: the Programmer's Stairway to Heaven</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/fizzbuzz-the-programmers-stairway-to-heaven/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>Evidently writing about <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/why-cant-programmers-program/">the FizzBuzz problem</a> on a programming blog results in a nigh-irresistible urge to code up a solution. The comments <a href="http://discourse.codinghorror.com/t/fizzbuzz-solution-dumping-ground/1752">here</a>, <a href="http://www.digg.com/programming/Why_Can_t_Programmers_Program">on Digg</a>, and <a href="http://programming.reddit.com/info/16swb/comments">on Reddit</a> – nearly a thousand in total – are filled with <a href="http://www.haacked.com/archive/2007/02/27/Why_Cant_Programmers._Read.aspx">hastily coded</a> solutions to FizzBuzz. Developers are nothing if not compulsive problem solvers.</p>
<p>It certainly wasn't my intention, but a large portion of the audience interpreted <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/why-cant-programmers-program/">FizzBuzz</a> as a challenge. I suppose <strong>it's like walking into Guitar Center and yelling 'most guitarists can't play Stairway to Heaven!'</strong><sup>*</sup></p>
<p>You might be shooting for a rational discussion of Stairway to Heaven as a way to measure minimum levels of guitar competence. But what you'll get, instead, is a <em>blazing guitarpocalypse</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ironicsans.com/2007/01/celebrity_patents.html"><img src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/02/6a0120a85dcdae970b016766cb3699970b-800wi.png" border="0" alt="Eddie Van Halen's Patent" width="350" height="465"></a></p>
<p>I'm invoking the <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0105793/">Wayne's World</a> rule here: Please, <strong>No Stairway to Heaven</strong>.</p>
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FOt3r_aNNxE?start=27" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>FizzBuzz was presented as the lowest level of comprehension required to illustrate adequacy. There's no glory to be had in writing code that establishes a <em>minimum</em> level of competency. Even if you can write it in five different languages or in under 50 bytes of code.</p>
<p><strong>The whole point of the original article was to think about <em>why</em> we have to ask people to write FizzBuzz.</strong> The mechanical part of writing and solving FizzBuzz, however cleverly, is irrelevant. Any programmer who cares enough to read programming blogs is already far beyond such a simple problem. FizzBuzz isn't meant for us. It's the ones we can't reach – the programmers who don't read anything – that we're forced to give the FizzBuzz test to.</p>
<p>Good software developers, <a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/how-not-to-become-a-rockstar-programmer/">even the ones who think they are Rockstars</a>, don't play Stairway to Heaven. And instead of writing FizzBuzz code, they should be thinking about ways to prevent us from <em>needing</em> FizzBuzz code in the first place.</p>
<p>* via <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/jgalloway">Jon Galloway</a> and Steven Burch.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-02-27T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/fizzbuzz-the-programmers-stairway-to-heaven/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
