<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>How To Achieve Ultimate Blog Success In One Easy Step</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p><a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070715113357/http://www.knowing.net/PermaLink,guid,e5aadb98-0a69-44e3-94cb-0afa583b0c0e.aspx">Always Be Jabbing</a>. <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000809.html">Always Be Shipping</a>. <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000339.html">Always Be Firing</a>. It's the same advice, stated in different ways for different audiences.</p>
<blockquote>My theory is that lead generation derives from Google rank and that the best way to increase Google rank is to be like a professional fighter: neither jabs nor haymakers are enough. <strong>You must be always jabbing and you must regularly throw haymakers</strong>. Blog continuously to keep your hit-rate and link-traffic high and write longer pieces, containing the high-value words associated with your niche, occasionally.</blockquote>
<p>When people ask me for advice on blogging, I always respond with yet another form of the same advice: <strong>pick a schedule you can live with, and <em>stick to it</em>. Until you do that, none of the other advice I could give you will matter.</strong> I don't care if you <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000516.html">suck at writing</a>. I don't care if <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000536.html">nobody reads your blog</a>. I don't care if you have <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000297.html">nothing interesting to say</a>. If you can demonstrate a willingness to write, and a desire to keep continually improving your writing, you will eventually be successful.</p>
<p><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877701c02970c" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/10/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877701c02970c-pi.jpg" border="0" alt="rocky marciano postcard" width="305" height="480"></p>
<p>But success takes time – a <em>lot</em> of time. I'd say a year at minimum. That's the element that weeds out so many impatient people. I wrote this blog for a year in utter obscurity, but I kept at it because I enjoyed it. I made a commitment to myself, under the banner of personal development, and I planned to meet that goal. My schedule was six posts per week, and <strong>I kept jabbing, kept shipping, kept firing</strong>. Not every post was that great, but I invested a reasonable effort in each one. Every time I wrote, I got a little better at writing. Every time I wrote, I learned a little more about the topic, how to research topics effectively, where the best sources of information were. Every time I wrote, I was slightly more plugged in to the rich software development community all around me. Every time I wrote, I'd get a morsel of feedback or comments that I kept rolling up into future posts. Every time I wrote, I tried to write something just the <em>tiniest bit</em> better than I did last time.</p>
<p>The changes, to me, were almost imperceptible. But from a very modest start – a 2004 new year's resolution for professional development – I'd say writing this blog is now, without a doubt, <em>the most important thing I've ever done in my entire career</em>.</p>
<p>I won't say I got <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000979.html">my job here at Vertigo</a> back <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000280.html">in 2005</a> because of this blog, but it was definitely a factor. I was <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000847.html">interviewed on .NET rocks</a>, and I've been interviewed online not <a href="http://www.dailyblogtips.com/interview-with-jeff-atwood-from-coding-horror/">once</a> but <a href="http://scribesonic.com/Blog/Archive/2007/10/04/Coding-Horror-Interview.aspx">twice</a>. I've been invited to speak at conferences. I am approached for <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000971.html">book deals</a> every few months. I exchange email regularly with Steve McConnell, one of my programming idols as a young adult, and he once asked <em>me</em> for advice on blogging. Joel Spolsky actually <em>recognized me</em> and invited conversation when I attended the Emeryville leg of his world tour. Charles Petzold sent me, completely unprompted, <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000934.html">a signed copy of his latest book</a>. People offer to send me <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000959.html">incredibly cool free swag</a> on a regular basis.</p>
<p>As near as I can tell, between RSS stats and log stats, <strong>around 100,000 people read this blog every day</strong>. Ad revenues that I've only <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000893.html">reluctantly taken</a> are significant enough now that I've actually entertained the idea, in my weaker moments, of becoming a full-time blogger. <em>That</em> is how crazy it's gotten. I would never have predicted this outcome in a million years, and writing it all down like this actually freaks me out a little bit.</p>
<p>I mention these things not because I'm a big fat showoff (or at least that's not the <em>only</em> reason), but because I achieved all this <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000187.html">without being particularly talented</a>. It was done one small post at a time, with no real planning or strategy whatsoever, beyond the simple incremental <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000530.html">suck less every year</a> kind. I am continually amazed and completely humbled by the success of this blog. All it took was a basic commitment to <em>keep</em> jabbing, <em>keep</em> shipping, <em>keep</em> firing.</p>
<p>If anything, what I've learned is this: <strong>if I can achieve this kind of success with my blog, so can you</strong>. So if you're wondering why the first thing I ask you when I meet you is "do you have a blog?" or "why don't you post to your blog more regularly?", or "could you turn that into a blog post?", now you know why. It's not just because I'm that annoying blog guy; it's because I'd like to wish the kind of amazing success I've had on everyone I meet.</p>
<p><a href="http://comics.com/pearls_before_swine/2008-11-16/"><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877707709970c" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/10/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877707709970c-pi.png" border="0" alt="blog comic 255548 full" width="640" height="299"></a></p>
<p>I'm just trying to share <strong>my easy one step plan to achieve Ultimate Blog Success</strong>: find a posting schedule you can live with, and stick to it for a year. Probably several years. Okay, so maybe that one step is really not quite so easy as I made it out to be. But everyone has to start somewhere, and the sooner the better.</p>
<p>So when was the last time <em>you</em> wrote a blog post?</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-10-26T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
