<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>We Are Typists First, Programmers Second</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/we-are-typists-first-programmers-second/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>Remember last week when I said <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001184.html">coding was just writing?</a></p>
<p>I was wrong. As one commenter noted, it's even simpler than that.</p>
<blockquote><p>[This] reminds me of a true "Dilbert moment" a few years ago, when my (obviously non-technical) boss commented that he never understood why it took months to develop software. "After all", he said, "it's just typing."</p></blockquote>
<p>Like broken clocks, even pointy-haired managers are right once a day. <strong>Coding is just typing.</strong></p>
<p><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777073f3970c" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777073f3970c-pi.jpg" border="0" alt="keyright keyboard" width="500" height="180"></p>
<p>So if you want to become a great programmer, start by becoming a great typist. <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/09/programmings-dirtiest-little-secret.html">Just ask Steve Yegge</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I can't understand why professional programmers out there allow themselves to have a career without teaching themselves to type. It doesn't make any sense. It's like being, I dunno, an actor without knowing how to put your clothes on. It's showing up to the game unprepared. It's coming to a meeting without your slides. Going to class without your homework. Swimming in the Olympics wearing a pair of Eddie Bauer Adventurer Shorts.</p>
<p>Let's face it: it's <em>lazy</em>.</p>
<p>There's just no excuse for it. There are no excuses. I have a friend, John, who can only use one of his hands. He types 70 wpm. He invented his own technique for it. He's not making excuses; he's typing circles around people who are making excuses.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I had a brief email exchange with Steve back in March 2007, after I wrote <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/03/going-commando---put-down-the-mouse.html">Put Down The Mouse</a>, where he laid that very same <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0105236/quotes?qt=qt0349153">Reservoir Dogs quote</a> on me. Steve's <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/09/programmings-dirtiest-little-secret.html">followup blog post</a> was a very long time in coming. I hope Steve doesn't mind, but I'd like to pull two choice quotes directly from his email responses:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I was trying to figure out which is the most important computer science course a CS student could ever take, and eventually realized it's Typing 101.</p>
<p>The really great engineers I know, the ones who build great things, they can type.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Strong statements indeed. I concur. <strong>We are typists first, and programmers second.</strong> It's very difficult for me to take another programmer seriously when I see them using the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Typing#Hunt_and_peck">hunt and peck typing techniques</a>. Like Steve, I've seen this far too often.</p>
<p>First, a bit of honesty is in order. Unlike Steve, I am a completely self-taught typist. I didn't take any typing classes in high school. Before I wrote this blog post, I realized I should check to make sure I'm not a total hypocrite. So I went to <a href="http://www.typeonline.co.uk/typingspeed.php">the first search result for typing test</a> and gave it a shot.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.typeonline.co.uk/typingspeed.php"><img src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/11/6a0120a85dcdae970b016766083705970b-pi.png" border="0" alt="typing test speed (WPM) results" width="593" height="92"></a></p>
<p>I am by no means the world's fastest typist, though <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000372.html">I do play a mean game of Typing of the Dead</a>. Let me emphasize that <em>this isn't a typing contest</em>. I just wanted to make sure I wasn't full of crap before I posted this. Yes, there's a first time for everything. Maybe this'll be the start of a trend. Doubtful, but you never know.</p>
<p>Steve and I believe there is nothing more fundamental in programming than the ability to efficiently express yourself through typing. Note that I said "efficiently" not "perfectly". This is about <strong>reasonable competency at a core programming discipline</strong>.</p>
<p>Maybe you're not convinced that typing is a core programming discipline. I don't blame you, although I do reserve the right to wonder how you manage to program without using your keyboard.</p>
<p>Instead of answering directly, let me share one of my (many) personal foibles with you. At least four times a day, I walk into a room having <em>no idea</em> why I entered that room. I mean no idea whatsoever. It's as if I have somehow been teleported into that room by an alien civilization. Sadly, the truth is much less thrilling. Here's what happened: in the brief time it took for me to get up and move from point A to point B, I have totally forgetten whatever it was that motivated me to get up at all. Oh sure, I'll rack my brain for a bit, trying to remember what I needed to do in that room. Sometimes I remember, sometimes I don't. In the end, I usually end up making multiple trips back and forth, remembering something else I <em>should</em> have done while I was in that room after I've already left it.</p>
<p>It's all quite sad. Hopefully your brain has a more efficient task stack than mine. But I don't fault my brain – I fault my body. It can't keep up. If I had arrived faster, I wouldn't have had time to forget.</p>
<p>What I'm trying to say is this: <em>speed matters</em>. <strong>When you're a fast, efficient typist, you spend less time between thinking that thought and expressing it in code.</strong> Which means, if you're me at least, that you might actually get <em>some</em> of your ideas committed to screen before you completely lose your train of thought. Again.</p>
<p>Yes, you should think about what you're doing, obviously. Don't just type random gibberish as fast as you can on the screen, unless you're a Perl programmer. But all other things being equal – and they never are – the touch typist <em>will</em> have an advantage. The best way to become a touch typist is through typing, and lots of it. A little research and structured practice couldn't hurt either. Here are some links that might be of interest to the aspiring touch typist:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://play.typeracer.com/">Type Racer</a> </li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.popcap.com/games/free/typershark">Typer Shark</a> </li>
<li>
<a href="http://haacked.com/archive/2007/06/05/dvorak-keyboard-layout-of-champions.aspx">Dvorak, Keyboard Layout of Champions</a> </li>
<li>
<a href="http://colemak.com/">Colemak keyboard layout</a> </li>
<li>
<a href="http://typera.tk/">TyperA</a> </li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.daskeyboard.com/">Das Keyboard</a> with blank keys </li>
<li>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Typing_of_the_Dead">The Typing of the Dead</a> (for PC) </li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/03/going-commando---put-down-the-mouse.html">Put Down That Mouse</a>. Seriously. It's a crutch. </li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.sightseekerstudio.com/yanmani/typingmania4.html">Typingmania</a> (warning, Japanophiles only) </li>
</ul>
<p>(But this is a meager and incomplete list. What tools do <em>you</em> recommend for becoming a better typist?)</p>
<p>There's precious little a programmer can do without touching the keyboard; it is the primary tool of our trade. I believe in <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000954.html">practicing the fundamentals</a>, and <strong>typing skills are as fundamental as it gets for programmers.</strong></p>
<p>Hail to the typists!</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-11-17T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/we-are-typists-first-programmers-second/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
