<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Steve Mann, Cyborg</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/steve-mann-cyborg/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I may have an unusual affinity for hardware, but <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Mann">Steve Mann</a> is in a class of his own. <a href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=technology&amp;res=940CE0D71239F937A25750C0A9649C8B63">He lives the hardware</a>. Steve Mann may be the world's original cyborg.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Mann">Steve Mann</a>, an engineering professor at the University of Toronto, has lived as a cyborg for more than 20 years, wearing a web of wires, computers and electronic sensors that are designed to augment his memory, enhance his vision and keep tabs on his vital signs.
</blockquote>
<p>
Mr. Mann has been exploring the frontiers of wearable computers since 1980.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Steve Mann, wearable computers from 1980-1998" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d93cd970b" height="366" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d93cd970b-pi.jpg" width="780">
</p>
<p>
Steve is <a href="http://www.wearcam.org/wearhow/node1.html">evidently at version 7</a> of his wearable computer. I'm surprised he hasn't updated the rig since 1999.
</p>
<p>
There was a flurry of interest in his work in 2001, which coincided with a <a href="http://wearcam.org/cyborg.htm">book</a> and a <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0301145/">movie</a> made about Steve. There's a companion <a href="http://www.linuxdevices.com/articles/AT8144626322.html">article on LinuxDevices</a> describing how to build a similar rig from 2001, but it feels ancient by today's standards.
</p>
<p>
It's hard to tell what's currently happening in the field of wearable computing. <a href="http://wearcam.org/">Steve's personal web page</a> is a shambles; nothing is dated. The <a href="http://www.media.mit.edu/wearables/">MIT wearable computing page</a> hasn't been updated since 2005, and the <a href="http://about.eyetap.org/index.shtml">Wearable Computing home</a> appears to be in a state of limbo. At least <a href="http://www.redwoodhouse.com/wearable/">Andy's wearable computing resource</a> looks like it's being updated on a regular basis.
</p>
<p>
Somehow, I thought the cyborgs would have a more compelling web presence.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-07-12T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/steve-mann-cyborg/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
