<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Blogging about Blogging</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/blogging-about-blogging/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I've avoided the incestuous nature of <a href="http://haacked.com/archive/2005/03/13/2357.aspx">blogging about blogging</a> until now, but the topic does come up occasionally. Not everyone is a believer in the utility of blogs; I was a skeptic only two years ago, and Michael Brundage went out of his way late last year to point out that his web site <a href="http://www.qbrundage.com/michaelb/pubs/essays/this_is_not_a_blog.html">is not a blog</a>. <b>What makes a blog worth reading?</b> I think Rory nailed it with <a href="http://neopoleon.com/blog/posts/13268.aspx%0A">his simple list of qualifications</a>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>you have to <b>want to write</b>
</li>
<li>you have to <b>believe you have something to say</b>
</li>
<li>you have to <b>have an interesting way of saying it</b>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
This is excellent advice, and it cuts to the heart of the question-- you should write blog entries because you are compelled to. If writing a blog entry feels like work to you, or if if you're worried about satisfying anyone other than yourself, then you'll have a difficult time maintaining a blog.
</p>
<p>
<b>Blogs are interesting because they are honest windows into other people's interests and passions.</b> As it turns out, the world is full of fascinating, extremely smart people. The opportunity to learn what motivates, interests and excites them-- professionally or personally-- is invaluable. And often in a purely practical sense. I've found an answer to a Google query in a blog entry more than once. </p>
<p>
I will add two riders to Rory's excellent guidelines:
</p>
<ul>
<li>you have to <b>be a decent (not great, but decent) writer</b><br>
<br>
I'm not the greatest writer, but I know bad writing when I see it. The deck is stacked heavily against you if you can't meet the basic grammar, spelling, and style rules of readable English. You have to be 10/10 in the other areas to overcome truly bad writing. Unfortunately, writing is a hard skill to develop. People literally spend lifetimes becoming better writers. However, the more writing you do-- and the more input you solicit on your writing-- the better you'll get at it. I also find that people who read a lot tend to be better writers. The next best thing to actually writing is reading a lot of good writers. One of my favorite pieces is Martin Luther King Jr.'s <a href="http://www.elise.com/quotes/webwisdom/LetterFromBirminghamJail.htm">Letter from a Birmingham Jail</a>, which I re-read every year. It's amazing on so many levels.<br>
<br>
</li>
<li>you have to <b>enable blog comments</b><br>
<br>
A blog without comments is not a blog. Period. If there's no two-way communication-- if readers of your blog can't politely point out that <i>you're full of crap</i>-- then whatever you're writing may be great, but it isn't a blog. Without the social dialog of feedback, you're merely publishing-- and publishing is something newspapers have been doing for hundreds of years.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-05-20T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/blogging-about-blogging/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
