<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>The Problem With Tabbed Interfaces</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-problem-with-tabbed-interfaces/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>Cyrus Najmabadi*  <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/cyrusn/archive/2005/04/10/406971.aspx">hates tabs in web browsers</a>:</p>
<blockquote>Ok, I seriously don't get tabs on Windows.  Hell, I don't get tabs on OSX either.  In the latter there's a great system called Expos, and in the former the taskbar does the job.  Once I start using tabs, things go all to hell. On OSX, I can't tell which FireFox/Safari window has the tab I want (since it's too small). In Windows I find myself scanning the taskbar for a site I was looking at, but I can't find it because the taskbar only lists the currently active tab.  This makes it so difficult to actually find the site I want and it ends up being far slower than just having a window available for each site.</blockquote>
<p>Initially I disagreed with Cyrus. However broken tabbed browsing may be, it's still a better solution than any of the existing alternatives. For example, Microsoft's own flagship Office suite, even today, suffers from some <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000262.html">highly inconsistent, bizarre pseudo-MDI behavior</a> for multiple documents. I'll take simple, reliable tabs over oddball MDI <em>any</em> day. No contest.</p>
<p>Lately I'm starting to come around to Cyrus' way of thinking. I don't hate tabbed interfaces-- yet-- but I definitely see what Cyrus was talking about. Tabs are increasingly the source of two aggravating mistakes for me:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<strong>I inadvertently open multiple copies of a web site</strong>, because I can't see that I already had that web site open in an obscured tab of an existing browser window. </li>
<li>
<strong>I accidentally close a browser window containing information that I needed</strong>, because the information was in an obscured tab of that particular browser window. </li>
</ol>
<p>In a tabbed interface, it's difficult to see anything except the active tab at any given time. <strong>Tabbed interfaces obscure as much as they organize.</strong> Tabs are great in moderation, but once they become a keystone navigational technique of your core applications, something peculiar happens. As Cyrus so aptly said, "once I start using tabs [extensively], things go all to hell."</p>
<p>Allow me to illustrate with an example. Let's say <strong>I want to check my GMail account</strong>, which I do frequently throughout the day. It's likely I already have GMail running, somewhere, so job #1 is to find it.</p>
<p>First, I scan the text in the taskbars. I use <a href="http://www.realtimesoft.com/ultramon/">UltraMon</a>, so each of my three monitors has its own distinct taskbar, summarizing every window on that monitor.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/taskbar-scanning.png" border="0" alt="taskbar" width="646" height="30"></p>
<p>But I don't see the word "GMail" in any of the three taskbars.</p>
<p>Next, I press ALT+TAB-- the poor man's Expos-- and scan through thumbnails of all the windows I have open. Do I see anything that looks like GMail?</p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1030/1341390026_bd0225a693_o.jpg"><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86da50e970b" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/09/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86da50e970b-pi.jpg" border="0" alt="desktop-alt-tab-small" width="635" height="365"></a></p>
<p>No. I don't see the distinctive look of the GMail user interface in any of those thumbnails. I've actually <a href="http://blogs.vertigo.com/personal/jatwood/Blog/Lists/Posts/Post.aspx?ID=31">enlarged the Alt+Tab thumbnail size via registry tweaks</a>, so this is as good as it gets for visibility. Squinting doesn't help.</p>
<p>The Alt+Tab dialog only uses the primary monitor, even though I have a three-monitor configuration. But we can harness the entire screen area of <em>all</em> the monitors if we install <a href="http://insentient.net/">the amazing Switcher</a>. I have Switcher mapped to Windows+Tab, replacing the <em>incredibly</em> lame <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/products/windowsvista/features/details/flip3D.mspx">Flip3D</a>. This is functionally identical to the OSX Expose that Cyrus mentioned. <em>Now</em> can I find GMail?</p>
<p><a href="http://img385.imageshack.us/img385/1773/desktopswitcherlargeiq7.jpg"><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86da527970b" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/09/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86da527970b-pi.jpg" border="0/" alt="desktop-switcher-small" width="832" height="240"></a></p>
<p>No. Even with the additional resolution of Switcher across all three monitors, I don't see GMail in any of the windows. At this point I would usually launch the URL using <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000766.html">the keyboard entry area of the Vista Start Menu</a>.  I could use the fancy <a href="http://brandontools.com/content/StartPlusPlus.aspx">Start++ add-in</a> to make this easier, but the vanilla Vista menu works well enough.</p>
<p>But wait! <em>I actually had GMail open already.</em> I've made a mistake.. again. I have <em>two</em> copies of GMail running now. Did you see it? Here, let me show you:</p>
<p><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86da536970b" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/09/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86da536970b-pi.png" border="0" alt="desktop-switcher-closeup.png" width="222" height="113"></p>
<p>That muddy, tiny little morass of pixels is the <em>only</em> visual indication that I already had GMail running as a tab in an existing browser instance. It's not in the taskbar, it's hardly visible at all in the small Alt+Tab screenshot, and you'd need the Six Million Dollar Man's bionic eye to see that <em>barely</em> visible tab in Expose, I mean, Switcher.</p>
<p>The depressing thing is that it's usually <em>faster</em> to mindlessly launch a new browser than it is to go through this tedious routine of playing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where's_Waldo">Where's Waldo</a> with (n) browsers and (n) tabs. And that's what I often do. But it bothers me.</p>
<p>Let me be very clear-- <strong>I like tabs</strong>. I think they're a far better option than the terrible MDI-alike alternatives. But I also think tabbed interfaces present some pretty severe navigational problems of their own. In the above example, if GMail had been in its own browser window, I could have found it instantly by looking in the taskbar, or at worst, by visually selecting it from even a smallish thumbnail image. Because GMail was in a tab, I wasted my time trying to find it, and I wasted even more time needlessly launching another browser. And this isn't an isolated incident. This happens to me <em>every day</em>. More times than I'd care to admit.</p>
<p>So how can we fix this? <strong>How can we integrate tabs with the existing navigational features of the operating system, such as the taskbar, and Expose?</strong> I keep coming back to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000595.html">search as the dominant computing metaphor</a>. The only thing I can think of is a plain-text search facility where I type "Gmail", and the OS would automatically highlight that tab (or window) and bring it to the front. That presupposes a very high level of integration between the application tabs and the operating system, however.</p>
<p>Despite the undeniable convenience of tabs for grouping and organizing related topics together in a single browser instance, I feel like tabs create as many problems for me as they solve. I wish I could "tear off" tabs into standalone windows on demand, too. That might be a reasonable workaround in the meantime.</p>
<p>* whatever happened to Cyrus? The last entry on his blog is two years old, and I can't find hide nor hair of him via internet searches. It's a shame, because I thoroughly enjoyed his blog.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-09-06T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-problem-with-tabbed-interfaces/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
