<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Configuring The Stack</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/configuring-the-stack/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
A standard part of my development kit is <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/">Microsoft's Visual Studio</a>. Here's what I have to install to get a current, complete version of Visual Studio 2005 on a new PC:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Visual Studio 2005 Team Suite Edition
</li>
<li>Visual Studio Team Explorer (Team Foundation Client)
</li>
<li>Visual Studio 2005 Service Pack 1
</li>
<li>Visual Studio 2005 Service Pack 1 Update for Windows Vista
</li>
<li>SQL Server 2005 Express Service Pack 2
</li>
<li>Visual Studio 2005 Team Edition for Database Professionals
</li>
<li>Visual Studio 2005 Team Edition for Database Professionals Service Pack 1
</li>
</ol>
<p>
Note that this is only a <i>partial</i> list; it doesn't include any of the other Visual Studio add-ons you might need to code against newer Microsoft technologies, such as <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?familyid=ca9d90fa-e8c9-42e3-aa19-08e2c027f5d6&amp;displaylang=en">ASP.NET AJAX</a>, <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyId=5D61409E-1FA3-48CF-8023-E8F38E709BA6&amp;displaylang=en">WF</a>, or <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyId=F54F5537-CC86-4BF5-AE44-F5A1E805680D&amp;displaylang=en">.NET 3.0</a>.
</p>
<p>
What's wrong with this picture?
</p>
<p>
I appreciate that some of these products were released out of order, which is partially why the install is so convoluted. But if one of the disadvantages of open-source software is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solution_stack">"configuring the stack"</a>, <b>I'm having a hard time seeing how Microsoft's commercial stack is any easier to configure than the alternative open source stacks these days</b>. Either the open source stuff has gotten a lot more streamlined and mature, or the Microsoft stuff is somehow devolving into complexity. I'm not sure which it is, exactly, but the argument that choosing a commercial development stack saves you time rings more and more hollow over time.
</p>
<p>
As the old adage goes, <i>Linux is only free if your time is worthless</i>*. But apparently your time can be worthless even if you've paid for the privilege.
</p>
<p>
* attributed to <a href="http://www.jwz.org/">Jamie Zawinski</a>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-08-03T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/configuring-the-stack/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
