<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>The Mysterious Cone of Uncertainty</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-mysterious-cone-of-uncertainty/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
One of the central themes in McConnell's <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0735605351/codihorr-20">Software Estimation: Demystifying the Black Art</a> is the ominously named <b>Cone of Uncertainty</b>. The cone defines statistically predictible levels of project estimate uncertainty at each stage of the project.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="The Cone of Uncertainty!" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd03b970c" height="290" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd03b970c-pi.png" width="531">
</p>
<p>
The cone has several ramifications, the most important of which is that <b>early project estimates will always be wildly inaccurate</b>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
As you can see from the graph, estimates created very early in the project are subject to a high degree of error. Estimates created at initial concept time can be inaccurate by a factor of 4x on the high side, or 4x on the low side.
</blockquote>
<p>
That means the total estimate range is a staggering 16x at the time of initial concept! And believe it or not, that's a <i>best case</i> scenario:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
An important-- and difficult-- concept is that The Cone of Uncertainty represents the best-case accuracy that is possible to have in software estimates at different points in a project. <b>It is easily possible to do worse.</b> It isn't possible to be more accurate; it's only possible to be more lucky.
</blockquote>
<p>
Furthermore, the cone doesn't narrow itself. If you don't actively work to reduce the variability of your project*, the cone of uncertainty quickly becomes a cloud of uncertainty. When will the software be done? <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_Nukem_Forever#Development_timeline">Who knows</a>. That's one reason for the <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000588.html">long, dismal history of software project failure</a>.
</p>
<p>
You may also be familiar with this software proverb:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
The first ninety percent of the task takes ninety percent of the time, and the last ten percent takes the other ninety percent.
</blockquote>
<p>
Getting trapped in the Cone of Uncertainty is a classic software project mistake. You think you're <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000889.html">99 percent done for months</a>. It's a cruel failure of perspective that's endemic to the profession of software development.
</p>
<p>
It reminds me of the popular <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mystery_Spot">Mystery Spot</a> tourist attraction in nearby Santa Cruz.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="mystery-spot.png" border="0" height="73" src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/mystery-spot.png" width="367">
</p>
<p>
I've been there. The Mystery Spot is a tacky tourist attraction, sure, but it's fun. And even if you're a complete skeptic and card-carrying Mensa member, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ames_Room">Ames Room</a> illusion is incredibly convincing when you, and everyone around you, is standing in it.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Ames Room illusion diagram" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd044970c" height="338" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fd044970c-pi.png" width="345">
</p>
<p>
Are you really 99 percent done? Or is your entire project stuck in the early, distorted part of the Cone of Uncertainty where you only <i>look</i> 99 percent done? Sometimes it's awfully difficult to tell the difference.
</p>
<p>
* This is something the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0735605351/codihorr-20">book </a> goes into great detail on, naturally.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-06-28T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-mysterious-cone-of-uncertainty/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
