<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Changing the Windows XP Boot Screen</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/changing-the-windows-xp-boot-screen/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
We're in the middle of an after-hours <a href="http://www.mame.net/">MAME</a> arcade project at work*. As one of the final fit and finish steps, I did a bit of research on how to <b>replace the default Windows XP boot screen</b> with something a little more arcade-y. I came up with StarDock's excellent <a href="http://www.stardock.com/products/bootskin/">BootSkin</a>:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="BootSkin screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67df970b" height="432" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/10/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d67df970b-pi.png" width="414">
</p>
<p>
This free app makes it painless to swap out your Windows XP boot screen or even create your own. The only downside is that you're <b>limited to a 16 color 640x480 image</b>. Thankfully, that's 16 colors of your choice, not the classic default 16 "Windows" colors. This appears to be a technical limitation of the XP boot process itself. The app packages up the images into "bootskins", which are simply zip files with a .bootskin extension.
</p>
<p>
There are a few hundred <a href="http://www.wincustomize.com/Skins.aspx?LibID=32">user created bootskins</a> to choose from at WinCustomize. I found a <b>Windows 1.01 bootskin</b>, but the author didn't do a good job of scaling the image, so it looked horrible. I reformatted it so it's pixel perfect:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/files/Windows101.bootskin.zip">Windows 1.01 bootskin</a> (3kb, remove .zip extension after download)
</li>
</ul>
<p>
If you're worried about the effects of this boot screen change, try it in a Virtual PC or VMWare image first. There's a similar StarDock app, <a href="http://www.stardock.com/products/logonstudio/">LogonStudio</a>, which allows you to customize the XP logon screen as well. I don't need to bother with this; our MAME computer automatically logs a user in via the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/downloads/powertoys/xppowertoys.mspx">TweakUI PowerToy</a> login tab.
</p>
<p>
* It's impressive. There will be more on this later.. ;)
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-10-01T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/changing-the-windows-xp-boot-screen/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
