<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>iTunes is Anti-Web</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/itunes-is-anti-web/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Ever find yourself clicking on links to music or videos and getting <b>blasted in the face with this delightful little number?</b>
</p>
<p>
<img alt="We are unable to find iTunes on your computer." border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877705b44970c" height="290" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877705b44970c-pi.png" width="414">
</p>
<p>
That's right -- links to any sort of music, TV shows, movies, podcasts, audiobooks or anything else available through Apple's iTunes store <i>requires custom software</i> to be installed on your computer before they will display thing one to you.
</p>
<p>
Is it so unreasonable to expect links in your browser to resolve to, oh, I don't know, <b>web pages containing information about the thing you just clicked on?</b> Is there anything more anti-web than demanding users install custom software to display information that could have just as easily been delivered through the browser?
</p>
<p>
So here's what we know:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Apple wants us to install iTunes.
</li>
<li>iTunes is necessary to sync media with Apple's iPods and iPhones.
</li>
<li>iTunes is only available for Windows and OS X.
</li>
<li>iTunes is required to browse or buy anything from the iTunes Store.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
That's all well and good for people who own iPods and iPhones -- and happen to be running Windows or OS X, I suppose.
</p>
<p>
But what about the rest of the world? Why lock them out with <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000881.html">the ultimate login barrier</a>? We might like to browse the iTunes Store, too. At the very least, I might want some basic information about the media I just clicked on. Right here in my browser where I already am. Information like what the heck it is, some artwork, maybe some audio clips, how much it costs -- sweet talk me. Make me want to buy it through the Apple Store. Dazzle me with your simplicity and ease of use. Beguile me with your wares!
</p>
<p>
Or, you could <b>bludgeon me with the digital equivalent of a giant stop sign</b>.
</p>
<p>
Hey, "it just works". Except when it doesn't.
</p>
<p>
I'm certainly able to click through to eminently purchaseable media on dozens of other places on the web using nothing more than my web browser. Let's imagine, for a moment, how utterly ridiculous it would be if I had to <b>install the Amazon application</b> to browse and purchase media from Amazon.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="unable to find Amazon on your computer" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877705b6e970c" height="290" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877705b6e970c-pi.png" width="414">
</p>
<p>
And yet this is exactly how the iTunes Store works. Or doesn't work, depending on your perspective.
</p>
<p>
I can understand requiring iTunes once you want to sync your media with Apple hardware devices -- although I would argue syncing should really be a fundamental, built in function of the operating system. But I'm not trying to sync anything! All I did was click on a link. It's <b>downright user hostile to demand installation of a special application merely to browse the store</b>, and it is most certainly against everything the web stands for and was built on.
</p>
<p>
The last "application" I can recall needing to install to get to things online was AOL.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.mikerichardson.name/oldaol/"><img alt="AOL 2.5 main menu" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877705ba4970c" height="362" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/07/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877705ba4970c-pi.png" width="514"></a>
</p>
<p>
And we all know <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000898.html">how great that turned out</a>.
</p>
<p>
For all the buzz about the Apple "it just works" mystique, the current iTunes Store design surely doesn't -- at least <b>not the same way the rest of the web does</b>. And I, for one, <a href="http://www.25hoursaday.com/weblog/2008/07/07/AListOfCompaniesWorkingHardToScrewUpMyWebExperience.aspx">can't get behind that</a>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-07-09T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/itunes-is-anti-web/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
