<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Snappy Answers to Stupid Programming Questions</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/snappy-answers-to-stupid-programming-questions/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>Here's a not-so-gentle reminder from David Pickett that <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/davidlem/archive/2006/05/16/598696.aspx">some programming interview questions</a> – in this case, "how would you write a routine to copy a file?" – are, well, <a href="http://exold.com/article/stupid-interview-questions">stupid</a>*:</p>
<blockquote>Q. What about the attributes?<br> A. Make the attributes the same.
<p>Q. Should I modify the attributes of the source file? If this file copy is part of a backup or archive operation, it'd probably be a mistake to leave the 'Archive' attribute on.<br> A. No, leave them as-is.</p>
<p>Q. What if the source file has the Archive attribute off? If I make it off on the new file as well, it could screw up the user's backup software.<br> A. Just make it the same. I don't care about the user's backup software.</p>
<p>Q. Well, I'm not sure that's the best approach to take when thinking about designing software FOR users, but if you say so.<br> A. ...</p>
<p>Q. What about compression? It's a file attribute, but the copy destination may not support compression.<br> A. Don't compress the copy.</p>
<p>Q. Even if the source is compressed, and the destination supports compression?<br> A. YES.</p>
<p>Q. What about encryption? What if the source file is encrypted, but the destination does not support encryption?<br> A. Don't encrypt the copy if the destination doesn't support it.</p>
<p>Q. Mmmmm, sorry, don't mean to digress, but … that could be a serious security hole. Especially if wherever this file copy function ends up supports arbitrary parameters (directly or indirectly).<br> A. <strong>Look, just copy the damn file.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>"How would you write a routine to copy a file" is just another <a href="http://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~wwu/riddles/intro.shtml">interview riddle</a>; it doesn't deserve a face value response. <a href="http://exold.com/article/stupid-interview-questions">David's answers</a> are even better-- they implode the question under its own weight.
</p>
<p>
<img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fcc3c970c" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fcc3c970c-pi.png" border="0" alt="Al Jaffee's Snappy Answers to Stupid Questions book cover" width="245" height="425">
</p>
<p>
The only rational answer to "how would you write a routine to copy a file?" is another question: <strong>why would any competent programmer ever write a file copy routine?</strong></p>
<p>The last time I checked, <a href="http://w-uh.com/articles/030524-moving_Mount_Fuji.html">moving mount Fuji</a> wasn't a part of our business plan, either.</p>
<p><small>* With apologies to Al Jaffee.</small></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-05-17T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/snappy-answers-to-stupid-programming-questions/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
