<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Road Warrior, Beyond Lapdom</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/road-warrior-beyond-lapdom/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
For all their cool teeny-tiny productiveness, I've never been able to effectively use a laptop on.. my lap. It's just not possible, except for brief sessions to check email or the like. To do real work, I have to find a desk or desk-like surface. This can be tough unless I'm in a hotel room.
</p>
<p>
I recently blogged about the <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000155.html">three essential travel accessories for my laptop</a>. Well, I am tentatively adding a fourth item to that list: <b>the portable laptop stand.</b> My mom picked this laptop stand thing up at a yard sale for a few bucks. She thought I might like it.* Initially I was quite skeptical-- how can something this ridiculous looking actually work? But it does! I can finally sit on the couch and work with my laptop at nearly full desktop speed, with a real mouse.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="PC Table Tote in action" height="275" src="http://www.pctabletote.com/images/projectr_table206.jpg" width="206">
</p>
<p>
I didn't get any documentation with the laptop stand, so I did some research and found out it's a <a href="http://www.pctabletote.com/">PC Table Tote</a>. Unfortunately, it's <a href="http://cart.bamart.com/addtocart.mart?m=pctabletote&amp;upc=111115555&amp;qty=1">a bit expensive at $49.99</a>. But it works unbelievably well, and <a href="http://www.pctabletote.com/images/caselegs.jpg">folds up into a neat little package</a>. I particularly like the way the opposite side mounts on the top to double the surface area, so you have a generous area for both laptop and mouse.
</p>
<p>
I'm no expert on devices like this, so there might be laptop stand <a href="http://instand.com/CR1/cr1.html">alternatives</a> that work just as well.  All I can tell you is,  it looks ridiculous, and it's a bit expensive, but this PC Table Tote thing really works.
</p>
<p>
* Thanks, mom. You rock.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2004-12-25T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/road-warrior-beyond-lapdom/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
