<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Would you rather be a Navigator or an Explorer?</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/would-you-rather-be-a-navigator-or-an-explorer/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
There's an interesting comment in this Amazon user review of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1556159390/105-1849539-8990040">The Microsoft Manual of Style for Technical Publications</a>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
My favorite entry, especially fun to find in light of Microsoft's legal problems arising in part from its relationship to Netscape Navigator, is this Orwellian directive, found on p. 185: "Navigate. Avoid the verb 'navigate' to refer to moving from site to site, page to page within a site, or link to link on the Internet. [...] Instead, use 'explore' to mean looking for sites or pages generally..."
</blockquote>
<p>
Would you rather be a Navigator or an Explorer? And what, exactly, is the implied meaning of this IE error:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="IE's Navigation Canceled error" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777004ec970c" height="339" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/01/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777004ec970c-pi.png" width="502">
</p>
<p>
The wording of the "Navigation Canceled" error message can't possibly have been a coincidence, given the intense rivalry with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netscape_Navigator">Netscape Navigator</a> back in the heady days of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Explorer">Internet Explorer</a> 3 and 4. The message now seems quaint in the wake of Netscape's near-irrelevance. Still, I wonder which cheeky little monkey at Microsoft came up with this particular error message way back when.
</p>
<p>
Of course, there's a long history of semi-friendly rivalry between Internet Explorer and its browser competition. In 1997, immediately after the release of Internet Explorer 4, <a href="http://home.snafu.de/tilman/mozilla/stomps.html">Microsoft dropped a giant IE logo on the Netscape campus</a>.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="The IE logo on Netscape's lawn" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777004f6970c" height="272" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/01/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128777004f6970c-pi.jpg" width="329">
</p>
<p>
And more recently, <a href="http://fredericiana.com/2006/10/24/from-redmond-with-love/">the Internet Explorer team sent the Firefox team a cake</a> to congratulate them on the release of Firefox 2.0.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Cake sent to Firefox team by IE team" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b012877700504970c" height="251" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/01/6a0120a85dcdae970b012877700504970c-pi.jpg" width="375">
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-01-24T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/would-you-rather-be-a-navigator-or-an-explorer/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
