<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>What's Wrong With Apple's Font Rendering?</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/whats-wrong-with-apples-font-rendering/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>I had read a few complaints that <a href="http://www.agileprogrammer.com/dotnetguy/archive/2006/06/03/15617.aspx">OS X font rendering was a little wonky</a>, even from <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2006/09/11.html">Joel Spolsky himself</a>:</p>
<blockquote>OS X antialiasing, especially, it seems, with the monospaced fonts, just isn't as good as Windows ClearType. Apple has some room to improve in this area; the fonts were blurry on the edges.</blockquote>
<p>I didn't believe it until I downloaded the first beta of Safari 3 for Windows and saw it for myself.</p>
<p>Font rendering in <a href="http://www.apple.com/safari/">Safari 3 Beta</a>:</p>
<p><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d908c970b" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d908c970b-pi.png" border="0" alt="Font rendering in Safari 3 beta for Windows" width="619" height="368"></p>
<p>Font rendering in <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/ie/default.asp">Internet Explorer 7</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d90b0970b-pi.png" border="0" alt="Font rendering in IE7" width="619" height="387"></p>
<p>All of these screenshots were taken under Windows Vista. It's easier to see what's happening if we zoom in a bit. These images are zoomed 200% with exact per-pixel resizing. Safari on the top, IE7 on the bottom:</p>
<p>
<img src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b015392886717970b-pi.png" border="0" alt="Font rendering in Safari, closeup" width="444" height="32">
<br>
<img src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/06/6a0120a85dcdae970b0154365c1608970c-pi.png" border="0" alt="Font rendering in IE7, closeup" width="440" height="32">
</p>
<p>At first I wasn't even sure if Apple was using <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/typography/ClearTypeInfo.mspx">ClearType</a>-alike RGB anti-aliasing, but it's clear from the zoomed image that they are. <strong>It looks like they've skewed the contrast of the fonts to an absurdly low level.</strong> The <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/typography/ClearTypePowerToy.mspx">ClearType Tuner PowerToy</a> allows you to manually adjust the RGB font aliasing contrast level, as I <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000651.html">documented in an earlier blog post</a>, but I don't think it can go as low as Apple has it set.</p>
<p><strong>I am absolutely not trying to start an <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000796.html">OS X versus Windows flame war</a> here</strong>. I used the quote above for a reason: there really is no single best way to render fonts; results depend on your display, the particular font you're using, and many other factors. That said, I'm curious why Apple's default font rendering strategies, <em>to my eye</em> -- and to the eyes of at least two other people -- are visibly inferior to Microsoft's on typical LCD displays. This is exactly the kind of graphic designer-ish detail I'd expect Cupertino to get right, so it's all the more surprising to me that they apparently haven't.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: red;">Update:</span></strong> I have a <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000885.html">followup post</a> that explains the font rendering difference. It looks like neither Apple or Microsoft is wrong; it's a question of whether you <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000885.html">respect the pixel grid</a>.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-06-11T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/whats-wrong-with-apples-font-rendering/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
