<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Coding Without Comments</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/coding-without-comments/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>If peppering your code with lots of comments is good, then having <b>zillions of comments</b> in your code must be <i>great</i>, right? Not quite. Excess is one way <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/when-good-comments-go-bad/">good comments go bad</a>:</p>
<pre>
'*************************************************
' Name: CopyString
'
' Purpose: This routine copies a string from the source
' string (source) to the target string (target).
'
' Algorithm: It gets the length of "source" and then copies each
' character, one at a time, into "target". It uses
' the loop index as an array index into both "source"
' and "target" and increments the loop/array index
' after each character is copied.
'
' Inputs: input The string to be copied
'
' Outputs: output The string to receive the copy of "input"
'
' Interface Assumptions: None
'
' Modification History: None
'
' Author: Dwight K. Coder
' Date Created: 10/1/04
' Phone: (555) 222-2255
' SSN: 111-22-3333
' Eye Color: Green
' Maiden Name: None
' Blood Type: AB-
' Mother's Maiden Name: None
' Favorite Car: <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-pontiac-aztek-and-the-perils-of-design-by-committee/">Pontiac Aztek</a>
' Personalized License Plate: "Tek-ie"
'*************************************************
</pre>
<p>I'm constantly running across comments from developers who don't seem to understand that the code already tells us <i>how</i> it works; <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/code-tells-you-how-comments-tell-you-why/">we need the comments to tell us <i>why</i> it works.</a> Code comments are so widely misunderstood and abused that you might find yourself wondering if they're worth using at all. Be careful what you wish for. Here's some code with <b>no comments whatsoever</b>:</p>
<pre>
r = n / 2;
while ( abs( r - (n/r) ) &gt; t ) {
  r = 0.5 * ( r + (n/r) );
}
System.out.println( "r = " + r );
</pre>
<p>Any idea what that bit of code does? It's perfectly readable, but <i>what the heck does it do?</i></p>
<p>Let's add a comment.</p>
<pre>
// square root of n with Newton-Raphson approximation
r = n / 2;
while ( abs( r - (n/r) ) &gt; t ) {
  r = 0.5 * ( r + (n/r) );
}
System.out.println( "r = " + r );
</pre>
<p>That must be what I was getting at, right? Some sort of pleasant, middle-of-the-road compromise between the two polar extremes of no comments whatsoever and carefully formatted epic poems every second line of code?</p>
<p>Not exactly. Rather than add a comment, I'd refactor to this:</p>
<pre>
private double SquareRootApproximation(n) {
  r = n / 2;
  while ( abs( r - (n/r) ) &gt; t ) {
    r = 0.5 * ( r + (n/r) );
  }
return r;
}
System.out.println( "r = " + SquareRootApproximation(r) );
</pre>
<p>I haven't added a single comment, and yet this mysterious bit of code is now perfectly understandable.</p>
<p>While comments are neither inherently good or bad, they are frequently used as a crutch. <b>You should always write your code as if comments didn't exist.</b> This <i>forces</i> you to write your code in the simplest, plainest, most self-documenting way you can humanly come up with.</p>
<p>When you've rewritten, refactored, and rearchitected your code a dozen times to make it easy for your fellow developers to read and understand – when you can't possibly imagine any conceivable way your code could be changed to become more straightforward and obvious – then, and <i>only then</i>, should you feel compelled to add a comment explaining what your code does.</p>
<p>As <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/02/portrait-of-n00b.html">Steve points out</a>, this is one key difference between junior and senior developers:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the old days, seeing too much code at once quite frankly exceeded my complexity threshold, and when I had to work with it I'd typically try to rewrite it or at least comment it heavily. Today, however, I just slog through it without complaining (much). When I have a specific goal in mind and a complicated piece of code to write, I spend my time making it happen rather than telling myself stories about it [in comments].</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Junior developers rely on comments to tell the story when they should be relying on the <em>code</em> to tell the story. Comments are narrative asides; important in their own way, but in no way meant to replace plot, characterization, and setting.</p>
<p>Perhaps that's the dirty little secret of code comments: <b>to write good comments you have to be a good writer</b>. Comments aren't code meant for the compiler, they're words meant to communicate ideas to other human beings. While I do (mostly) love my fellow programmers, I can't say that effective communication with other human beings is exactly our strong suit. I've seen three-paragraph emails from developers on my teams that practically melted my brain. <em>These</em> are the people we're trusting to write clear, understandable comments in our code? I think maybe some of us might be better off sticking to our strengths – that is, writing for the compiler, in as clear a way as we possibly can, and reaching for the comments only as a method of last resort.</p>
<p>Writing good, meaningful comments is hard. It's as much an art as writing the code itself; maybe even more so. As Sammy Larbi said in <a href="http://www.codeodor.com/index.cfm/2008/6/18/Common-Excuses-Used-To-Comment-Code-and-What-To-Do-About-Them/2293">Common Excuses Used To Comment Code</a>, if your feel your code is too complex to understand <i>without</i> comments, <b>your code is probably just bad.</b> Rewrite it until it doesn't need comments any more. If, at the end of that effort, you still feel comments are necessary, then by all means, add comments … carefully.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-07-24T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/coding-without-comments/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
