<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Blu-Ray: Is It Time?</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/blu-ray-is-it-time/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I've been monitoring the progress of high-definition video playback on the PC for quite a while now:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000747.html">Next-Gen DVD: Are Those Additional Pixels Worth Your Money?</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000746.html">High-Definition Video on the PC</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000758.html">Is Your PC Capable of Hi-Def?</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000756.html">Will Your Next Computer Monitor Be a HDTV?</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
It's been almost two years since I wrote that series, and I think we're <b>dangerously close to viable high definition video playback on typical, mainstream PCs</b>. One metric I follow closely is the price of the hardware, and OEM Blu-Ray drives are <a href="http://www.newegg.com/Product/Product.aspx?Item=N82E16827136154">now only $99 shipped</a>.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.newegg.com/Product/Product.aspx?Item=N82E16827136154"><img alt="LG GGC-H20LK Blu-Ray HD-DVD combo drive" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86e0fea970b" height="230" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2008/12/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86e0fea970b-pi.jpg" width="600"></a>
</p>
<p>
This drive is a DVD burner, in addition to playing HD-DVDs, Blu-Ray, and obviously DVDs -- and it also has very positive customer reviews. I couldn't resist, so I bought one.
</p>
<p>
I have no need for a standalone Blu-Ray player, but a cursory look tells me those are down to <a href="http://www.anrdoezrs.net/click-2338938-10440897?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.newegg.com%2FProduct%2FProduct.aspx%3FItem%3DN82E16882103400%26nm_mc%3DAFC-C8Junction%26cm_mmc%3DAFC-C8Junction-_-Blu-Ray%2BPlayers-_-Panasonic-_-82103400&amp;cjsku=N82E16882103400">around $250 for decent models</a>. And then of course there's always the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001COU9I6/?tag=codihorr-20">PlayStation 3 option</a>.
</p>
<p>
It's a shame OS X and Vista don't natively support HD playback of any kind (although Vista does include some copy protection mechanisms specific to high-definition video playback, which was the <a href="http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/pubs/vista_cost.html">source of great hue and outrage</a>). When you pair this $99 drive with some third party playback software like PowerDVD HD or WinDVD HD, you're set.
</p>
<p>
I'm particularly interested in high definition PC playback because the <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001107.html">home theater PC I recently built</a> is more than capable:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Built in HDMI out (on the motherboard)
</li>
<li>Onboard video that <a href="http://techreport.com/articles.x/14261/9">supports H.264 acceleration</a>
</li>
<li>A modern dual-core CPU
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Also, I finally own a true 1920 x 1080 HDTV now -- yes, you can all stop making fun of me for using a creaky old brass and steam powered 852 x 480 EDTV -- so all the pieces are now in place for me to adopt Blu-Ray. I switched my <a href="http://www.netflix.com/Genre/Blu-ray/2444">Netflix account over to Blu-Ray</a> this morning.
</p>
<p>
I'm not quite a high definition video early adopter, but I'm still on the leading edge of the curve. <b>Funny how technology cycles repeat themselves.</b> I distinctly recall being an early adopter of DVDs back in 1998, almost exactly 10 years ago. The 720 x 480 resolution and Dolby Digital sound seemed so impressive back then. I remember marvelling at the fancy interactive menus on the Austin Powers DVD. Of course, DVD quality is <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000124.html">pretty pedestrian by today's standards</a>. We've <i>almost</i> gotten to the point where DVD-level video quality is available worldwide in a typical web browser, not necessarily <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000755.html">through YouTube</a>, but <a href="http://www.vimeo.com/highdef">through Vimeo</a> and other alternatives.
</p>
<p>
With that in mind, I wonder how quaint Blu-Ray will seem in 2018?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2008-12-04T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/blu-ray-is-it-time/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
