<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Quad Core Desktops and Diminishing Returns</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/quad-core-desktops-and-diminishing-returns/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Dual core CPUs were <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000285.html">a desktop novelty in the first half of 2005</a>. Now, with the introduction of the <a href="http://www.apple.com/macpro/">Mac Pro</a> (see one <a href="http://www.powermax.com/articles_reviews/article.php?id=33">unboxed</a>), <b>dual core is officially pass</b>. Quad core-- at least in the form of two dual-core CPUs-- is where it's at for desktop systems.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Task Manager with 4 CPUs" border="0" height="94" src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/taskman-4-cpus.png" width="365">
</p>
<p>
And sometime early next year, the <a href="http://news.com.com/Intel+shows+off+its+quad+core/2100-1006_3-6038148.html">first true quad core CPUs will hit the market</a>.
</p>
<p>
I think there are clear multitasking benefits in a dual-core configuration for typical computer users. All you need to do is run two applications at once, and who doesn't do that these days?
</p>
<p>
However, <b>the benefits from moving to quad-core and beyond are less clear</b>. Effectively utilizing 4 or 8 CPU cores requires extremely aggressive multithreading support within applications. How aggressive? <i>Rewrite your entire application in a new language</i> aggressive. That's a <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000169.html">much more difficult problem</a>. It's also not a common optimization, except within very specific application niches.
</p>
<p>
Dual CPU desktop systems weren't twice as fast as single CPU desktop systems. But they were a substantial, worthwhile speed bump. <b>With quad CPU systems, we've hit the point of diminishing returns.</b>
</p>
<p>
Current benchmark data definitely bears this out. I distilled results from these <a href="http://www.gamepc.com/labs/view_content.asp?id=opteron275&amp;page=8">GamePC</a> and <a href="http://techreport.com/reviews/2005q2/opteron-x75/index.x?pg=6%0A">TechReport</a> reviews of the Opteron 275 (dual core 2.2 GHz), which also included the Opteron 247 (single core 2.2 GHz). <b>It's an apples-to-apples comparison between Dual and Quad configurations of an Athlon 64 running at the same speed-- 2.2 GHz.</b>
</p>
<p>
</p>
<table width="600">
<tr>
<td>
 </td>
<td>
<strong>Dual CPU</strong>
</td>
<td>
<strong>Quad CPU</strong>
</td>
<td>
 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
3D Studio Max 7.0 Radiosity Render</td>
<td>
239</td>
<td>
144</td>
<td>
<font color="red">1.7 x</font>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
POV-Ray chess2.pov</td>
<td>
144</td>
<td>
87</td>
<td>
<font color="red">1.6 x</font>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Cinebench 2003 Rendering</td>
<td>
571</td>
<td>
1021</td>
<td>
<font color="red">1.8 x</font>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Alias Maya 6.0 Zoo Render</td>
<td>
49</td>
<td>
43</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Photoshop CS Filter Benchmark</td>
<td>
146</td>
<td>
131</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Flash MX 2004 MPEG import</td>
<td>
37</td>
<td>
35</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Windows Media Encoder 9.0 MPEG to WMV</td>
<td>
125</td>
<td>
119</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Xmpeg/DivX encoding</td>
<td>
71</td>
<td>
75</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
LAME 3.97 WAV to MP3</td>
<td>
69</td>
<td>
67</td>
<td>
none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Apache 2.0 10k user stress test</td>
<td>
1397</td>
<td>
1478</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Apache 2.0 50k user stress test</td>
<td>
1346</td>
<td>
1875</td>
<td>
1.4 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Sysmark 2004</td>
<td>
226</td>
<td>
242</td>
<td>
1.1 x</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Half-Life 2: Airboat chase</td>
<td>
95</td>
<td>
96</td>
<td>
none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
Doom 3: Site 3 timedemo</td>
<td>
164</td>
<td>
166</td>
<td>
none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
3DMark05</td>
<td>
5244</td>
<td>
5244</td>
<td>
none</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
I eliminated most of the synthetic benchmarks; I tried to focus on real desktop applications that people actually use. The <a href="http://www.bapco.com/products/sysmark2004/">Sysmark 2004</a> results are particularly telling.
</p>
<p>
However, the results I did find are so poor that <b>I wonder if any quad CPU system is good for much more than bragging rights</b>. Of the desktop apps, only three truly benefit from a quad CPU configuration: 3D Studio Max, POV-Ray, and Cinebench 2003. Notice a pattern? Rendering and encoding tend to parallelize well.
</p>
<p>
Unless you're often running a specific application that is optimized for multithreading, there's no compelling reason to run out and buy a quad-CPU desktop system today. And I don't see that advice changing over the next few years. At least, not until the state of software development changes quite radically to embrace multithreading across the board.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-08-08T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/quad-core-desktops-and-diminishing-returns/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
