<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>C# Snippet Parity</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/c-snippet-parity/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Microsoft recently released a <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/downloads/codesnippets/default.aspx">complete set of C# code snippets for Visual Studio 2005</a>. This brings C# to parity with VB.NET, which had many more code snippets "in the box".
</p>
<p>
Unfortunately, Microsoft's installation strategy for these new snippets leaves a lot to be desired. You can download and "install" all the snippets at once, but you must manually add each of the snippet folders via the Snippet Manager (Ctrl+K, Ctrl+B). <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000419.html">I loves me some snippets</a>, but this is unacceptable!
</p>
<p>
The snippets themselves, of course, are just individual XML files that end in .snippet sitting in a bunch of folders. There are two valid snippet paths: per-user and system-wide. The system-wide C# snippet path is:
</p>
<p>
<code>C:Program FilesMicrosoft Visual Studio 8VC#Snippets1033</code>
</p>
<p>
There's an index file in that folder, <code>SnippetsIndex.xml</code>, which appears to store the snippet paths. You might think editing this file would cause the folders to appear in the snippet browser (Ctrl+K, Ctrl+X). Seems logical, right?
</p>
<p>
Unfortunately, it's not that easy.
</p>
<p>
I think that file <i>may</i> be used the first time the IDE is initialized, but edits to that file don't appear in the Snippet Manager.
</p>
<p>
The real snippet paths are stored in the registry at:
</p>
<p>
<code>[HKCUSoftwareMicrosoftVisualStudio8.0LanguagesCodeExpansionsVisual C#]</code>
</p>
<p>
Why they chose to store this stuff in the registry <i>and</i> in an XML file is beyond me. Anyway, I packaged the correctly pathed snippets and a registry file together. Now you can quickly get the snippets installed on your system without running a pointless installer that does virtually nothing for you.
</p>
<p>
You can go from tired ..
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Aww, C# has hardly any snippets" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d663f970b" height="192" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/02/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d663f970b-pi.png" width="275">
</p>
<p>
.. to wired ..
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Just like VB.NET snippets! Viva le squiggly!" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d665a970b" height="198" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/02/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d665a970b-pi.png" width="225">
</p>
<p>
.. in no time at all. If you've forgotten the keyboard shortcuts for snippets, revisit my <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000419.html">snippet blog entry</a> to refresh your memory.
</p>
<p>
Microsoft provides 295 new C# code snippets, and they're 508 KB in total size. I chose to package the snippets as a 7zip file for compression efficiency:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>ZIP: 229kb
</li>
<li>RAR: 73kb
</li>
<li>7Zip: 56kb
</li>
</ul>
<p>
To be fair to ZIP, it probably would have done better if the format supported <a href="http://www.win-rar.com/solidarchive.html">solid archiving</a> for this set of small files.
</p>
<p>
To decompress the archive, I recommend switching to <a href="http://www.rarlab.com/">WinRAR</a> if you aren't already. It supports 7zip as well as RAR and ZIP, but more importantly, it won the <a href="http://www.donationcoder.com/Reviews/Archive/ArchiveTools/index.html">best archive tool DonationCoder roundup</a>. I'm not a huge fan of the UI, but I encounter RAR files often enough that WinZIP isn't cutting it any more.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/files/ms-csharp-snippets.7z.zip">Download C# snippets and registry file</a> (60kb 7zip archive)
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-02-21T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/c-snippet-parity/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
