<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Designing Interactions at IDEO</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/designing-interactions-at-ideo/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>Recently, <a href="http://jcooney.net/">Joseph Cooney</a> and a coworker both recommended the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0262134748/codihorr-20">Designing Interactions</a> to me at the same time. A strange confluence of events that's got to be some sort of sign. I immediately ordered the book.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0262134748/codihorr-20"><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d970c970b" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d970c970b-pi.jpg" border="0" alt="Designing Interactions book cover" width="416" height="500"></a></p>
<p>And I'm so glad I did. It's a wonderful, beautiful book about the history of digital technology design, filled with stunning full-color photographs and illustrations, frequently interspersed with interviews from key industry figures. You can browse the table of contents and download a sample chapter from <a href="http://www.designinginteractions.com/">the book's website</a>. I recommend it without reservation.</p>
<p>I didn't realize it at the time, but the author, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Moggridge%20">Bill Moggridge</a>, is one of the co-founders of the iconic design firm <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IDEO">IDEO</a>. His other claim to fame is designing what many consider to be the world's first laptop computer in 1979, the <a href="http://oldcomputers.net/grid1101.html">GRiD Compass</a>. Nobody could afford it, of course, but it was an evolutionary milestone in computer history.</p>
<p>IDEO is a true giant in the field of design; just <a href="http://www.ideo.com/work/">browse through their portfolio</a> and I can practically guarantee you've used more than one product they've designed. IDEO is so influential they've packaged their message into products, too. I already own a few IDEO artifacts. I ordered the <a href="http://www.ideo.com/work/method-cards">IDEO Method Cards</a> back in 2005. I still occasionally flip through them; they're great little nudges to get you thinking about all the different ways design should influence what you're working on.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ideo.com/work/method-cards"><img class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9737970b" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2007/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d9737970b-pi.jpg" border="0" alt="IDEO Method Cards" width="428" height="450"></a></p>
<p>Last Christmas, without any coaching from me, my wife bought me another IDEO book, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0385499841/codihorr-20">The Art of Innovation: Lessons in Creativity</a>. It's a decent read as well. I have yet to obtain a copy of their latest book, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0385512074/codihorr-20">The Ten Faces of Innovation: IDEO's Strategies for Defeating the Devil's Advocate and Driving Creativity Throughout Your Organization</a>, but if the length of the title is any indication, I'm sure it's a doozy.</p>
<p>I think IDEO and Moggridge are on the right track: <strong>strictly framing technology in service to people</strong>. I know it seems obvious, but it's one of those things that bears reminding every so often. Perhaps that's why reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0262134748/codihorr-20">Designing Interactions</a> is so inspiring.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-05-15T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/designing-interactions-at-ideo/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
