<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Company of Heroes</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/company-of-heroes/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
My latest gaming obsession is the new <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real-time_strategy">real-time strategy</a> game, <a href="http://www.companyofheroesgame.com/">Company of Heroes</a>. It's easily one of the best games of the year for the PC. And it's quite possibly one of the best real-time strategy games ever made. To give you an idea of what I'm talking about, the game currently has <a href="http://www.gamerankings.com/htmlpages2/927618.asp">a 95% review average on GameRankings</a> with 13 reviews, which puts it squarely on track to be one of the top 10 best reviewed PC games <i>of all time</i>.
</p>
<p>
It's so good, in fact, that I was compelled to complete <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/company-of-heroes-all-campaign-medals.jpg">every optional objective</a> in the campaign missions.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Company of Heroes screenshot" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fefd4970c" height="442" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/09/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fefd4970c-pi.jpg" width="602">
</p>
<p>
The <a href="http://www.gamespot.com/promos/2006/companyofheroes-demo/index.html">Company of Heroes demo</a> is a whopping 1.8 gigabytes in size, but it offers a significant chunk of the game: unlimited, unlocked skirmish mode against the CPU and two single player maps.
</p>
<p>
Sure, the World War II genre has been done to death. But this is a real-time strategy game with incredible graphical detail, dynamic, destructible levels, and unparalleled unit intelligence and tactics. It elevates the entire real-time strategy genre to the next level.
</p>
<p>
Company of Heroes is the first new game I installed after installing Vista RC1. Coincidentally, it's also one of the first games with <a href="http://www.xploder.net/news/2297/Microsofts-Games-for-Windows-Plans.htm">Microsoft's "Games for Windows" certification</a>, which means (among other things) that it <a href="http://blogs.vertigosoftware.com/ericc/archive/2006/09/18/3700.aspx">integrates automatically into Vista's Games menu</a>.
</p>
<p>
Needless to say, highly recommended. If you've ever played and enjoyed an RTS game of any type, buy this game immediately. For everyone else, <a href="http://www.gamespot.com/promos/2006/companyofheroes-demo/index.html">get the demo</a> and try it yourself. I think you'll be impressed.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-09-21T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/company-of-heroes/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
