<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>The Programmer's Bill of Rights</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-programmers-bill-of-rights/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>It's unbelievable to me that a company would pay a developer $60—$100k in salary, yet cripple them with terrible working conditions and crusty hand-me-down hardware. This makes no business sense whatsoever. And yet I see it all the time. It's shocking how many companies still don't provide software developers with the essential things they need to succeed.</p>
<p>I propose we adopt a <strong>Programmer's Bill of Rights</strong>, protecting the rights of programmers by preventing companies from denying them the fundamentals they need to be successful.</p>
<img alt="The Bill of Rights" height="337" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/08/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fe067970c-pi.png" width="400">
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Every programmer shall have <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/multiple-monitors-and-productivity/">two monitors</a></strong></p>
<p>With the crashing prices of LCDs and the ubiquity of dual-output video cards, you'd be crazy to limit your developers to a single screen. The productivity benefits of doubling your desktop are <a href="https://developers.slashdot.org/story/03/10/09/137232/multiple-monitors-increase-productivity">well documented by now</a>. If you want to maximize developer productivity, make sure each developer has two monitors. <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/three-monitors-for-every-user/">Or three</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Every programmer shall have <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/building-a-pc-part-viii-iterating/">a fast PC</a></strong></p>
<p>Developers are required to run a lot of software to get their jobs done: development environments, database engines, web servers, virtual machines, and so forth. Running all this software requires a fast PC with lots of memory. The faster a developer's PC is, the faster they can cycle through debug and compile cycles. You'd be foolish to pay the extortionist prices for the extreme top of the current performance heap – but always make sure you're buying <em>near</em> the top end. Outfit your developers with fast PCs that have lots of memory. Time spent staring at a progress bar is <em>wasted time</em>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Every programmer shall have their choice of <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/my-mouse-fetish/">mouse</a> and <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-code-keyboard/">keyboard</a></strong></p>
<p>In college, I <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/are-you-following-the-instructions-on-the-paint-can/">ran a painting business</a>. Every painter I hired had to buy their own brushes. This was one of the first things I learned. Throwing a standard brush at new painters didn't work. The "company" brushes were quickly neglected and degenerated into a state of disrepair. But painters who bought their own brushes took care of them. Painters who bought their own brushes learned to appreciate the difference between the professional $20 brush they owned and cheap disposable dollar store brushes. Having their own brush engendered a sense of enduring responsibility and craftsmanship. Programmers should have the same relationship with their mouse and keyboard – they are the essential, workaday tools we use to practice our craft and should be treated as such.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Every programmer shall have <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/investing-in-a-quality-programming-chair/">a comfortable chair</a></strong></p>
<p>Let's face it. We make our livings largely by sitting on our butts for 8 hours a day. Why not spend that 8 hours in a comfortable, well-designed chair? Give developers chairs that make sitting for 8 hours not just tolerable, but enjoyable. Sure, you hire developers primarily for their giant brains, but don't forget your developers' <em>other</em> assets.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Every programmer shall have a fast internet connection</strong></p>
<p>Good programmers <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/never-design-what-you-can-steal/">never write what they can steal</a>. And the internet is the best conduit for stolen material ever invented. I'm <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/recommended-reading-for-developers/">all for books</a>, but it's hard to imagine getting any work done without fast, responsive internet searches at my fingertips.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Every programmer shall have <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/this-is-your-anti-productivity-pod/">quiet working conditions</a></strong></p>
<p>Programming requires focused mental concentration. Programmers cannot work effectively in an interrupt-driven environment. Make sure your working environment protects your programmers' <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">flow state</a>, otherwise they'll waste most of their time bouncing back and forth between distractions.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The few basic rights we're asking for are easy. They aren't extravagant demands. They're fundamental to the quality of work life for a software developer. If the company you work for isn't getting it right, making it right is neither expensive nor difficult. <strong>Demand your rights as a programmer!</strong> And remember: you can either change your company, or you can <em>change your company</em>.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-08-24T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-programmers-bill-of-rights/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
