<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Firefox Excessive Memory Usage</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/firefox-excessive-memory-usage/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I like Firefox. I've even grown to like it slightly more than IE6, mostly because it has a far richer add-on ecosystem.
</p>
<p>
But I have one serious problem with Firefox:
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Massive Firefox memory usage" border="0" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d65d0970b" height="159" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2006/03/6a0120a85dcdae970b0120a86d65d0970b-pi.png" width="662">
</p>
<p>
This screenshot was taken after a few days of regular Firefox usage. That's <b>over 900 megabytes of memory for a single, non-tabbed instance of Firefox</b>.
</p>
<p>
What's going on? Well, according to my tests, <b>Firefox never seems to release any of the memory it uses-- until you close <i>all</i> instances of Firefox.</b> If you spend enough time browsing the web, and never close Firefox completely, you'll consume nearly a gigabyte of memory!
</p>
<p>
Because I often keep at least one browser window open for research or reminder purposes, this bites me <i>a lot</i>. I'll look at Task Manager and Firefox will <b>regularly be gobbling up over 400 megabytes</b>. This isn't uncommon. It's normal.
</p>
<p>
I don't ever recall having this problem with IE 6.
</p>
<p>
Of course, I can close all instances of Firefox and reduce memory usage back to zero, but why should I have to? I've read <a href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/cmp/20060217/tc_cmp/180203308">this techweb news article</a> on the controversy around Firefox and memory usage, and I've implemented the workaround suggested in that article:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Within Firefox, enter "about:config" (minus the quotation marks) in the address bar
</li>
<li>Scroll down to the entry "browser.sessionhistory.max_total_viewers" and double-click it.
</li>
<li>In "Enter integer value" field, type..
<ul>
<li>"0" to disable the cache
</li>
<li>"1" through "8" to set the maximum cache as 1 through 8 previously-viewed pages
</li>
<li>"-1" to return the cache to its default
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
Sadly, this fix did very little to address the problem. The above screenshot was taken <i>after</i> setting that value to 1!
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-03-13T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/firefox-excessive-memory-usage/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
