<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Compiler, It Hurts When I Do This</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/compiler-it-hurts-when-i-do-this/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Here's a question that recently came up on an internal mailing list: <b>how do I create an enum with a name that happens to be a c# keyword?</b>
</p>
<p>
I immediately knew the answer for VB.net; you use brackets to delimit the word.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<pre language="vb.net">
Public Enum test
[Public]
[Private]
End Enum
Sub Main()
Dim e As test = test.Private
End Sub
</pre>
<p>
A little internet searching revealed that such things are called <b>escaped identifiers</b>, and the equivalent in c# is the @ character.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<pre language="c#">
public enum test
{
@public,
@private
}
static void main()
{
test e = test.@private;
}
</pre>
<p>
They do work the same, but they don't look the same. In c#, you have to type the unwanted escaped identifier every time you use the enum, and the enum even shows up with the @ prefix in intellisense. However, if you echo back the enum value, it will be "private", and not "@private", as expected.
</p>
<p>
However, after spending 30 minutes researching the answer and playing with the results, I began to wonder if the real answer to this question should be another question: <b>why do you need to do this?</b> At some point it all becomes a little ridiculous. What's next-- an enum named "enum"? A variable named "variable"?
</p>
<p>
Stop me if you've heard this one before:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
A man goes to a doctor's office. He says, "Doctor, it hurts when I raise my arm over my head."
<p>
The doctor replies, "Then don't raise your arm over your head."
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
If the compiler is telling you it hurts when you do something, maybe you should stop doing it. Just something to consider before merrily swimming your way upstream.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-07-26T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/compiler-it-hurts-when-i-do-this/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
