<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Secretly, We're All Geeks</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/secretly-were-all-geeks/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Scott Hanselman was kind enough to <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/RerediscoveringJeffAtwood.aspx">sing the praises of my blog</a> a few months ago, completely unprompted. I finally met Scott in person at TechEd this year, and I can assure you that if you suck, Scott will be the first person to <i>tell you</i> that you suck.* That's how he rolls, ese. So getting a thumbs up from Mr. Hanselman is hard-earned praise indeed, and I do appreciate it.
</p>
<p>
In the fine tradition of <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0223897/">paying it forward</a>, I want to pass on similar kudos to one of my favorite blogs-- <a href="http://secretgeek.net/">Leon Bambrick's secretGeek</a>.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://secretgeek.net/"><img alt="secretgeek" border="0" height="43" src="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/images/secretgeek-logo.png" width="156"></a>
</p>
<p>
Sure, there may be other blogs out there by authors who are <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/">better writers</a>, or who have <a href="http://wesnerm.blogs.com/">killer technical chops</a>, but Leon is all that stuff, and he's <i>consistently funny</i>, too. And not in an uncomfortable, soul-baring, More Than I Needed To Know <a href="http://www.neopoleon.com/blog/">Rory Blythe</a> kind of way, or in the highly unfortunate I Can't Believe This Passes For Humor way of <a href="http://www.userfriendly.org/">User Friendly</a>.
</p>
<p>
Secretly, we may all be geeks-- but very few geeks are as talented at walking the fine line of technical comedy as Mr. Leon Bambrick. It's all funny because it's all true. Take a few minutes to read through his archives and you'll <a href="http://secretgeek.net/Ruby_On_Rails_face.asp">see what I mean</a>.
</p>
<p>
* But in an amusing way, so you'll laugh at how much you suck, too. ;)
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2006-06-27T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/secretly-were-all-geeks/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
