<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Interactive Xpath Expression Builder</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/interactive-xpath-expression-builder/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
I use Xpath queries about once a year, so of course I completely forget the syntax every time I come back to it. And each time this happens, I somehow find <a href="http://pluralsight.com/blogs/aaron/">Aaron Skonnard's</a> very cool <b>web-based interactive Xpath Expression Builder</b>, which lets you hack on Xpath with real time visual feedback as you type. It's great. Except this time I couldn't find it!
</p>
<p>
I guess there's been a bit of a shakeup; Aaron works for PluralSight now. The top google hits for the interactive Xpath expression builder on the DevelopMentor site return a glorified 404 page. According to <a href="http://pluralsight.com/blogs/aaron/articles/173.aspx">his blog post</a>, all the DevelopMentor samples have been moved to <a href="http://www.theserverside.net/developmentor/index.tss">this confusing ServerSide.NET page</a>. And they're now distributed as zip files, which completely ruins the immediate feedback that made the interactive XPath builder pages so useful. For convenience, <b>I put the XPath Expression Builder pages up on this server</b>:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/xpath/1.0/">Interactive XPath Expression Builder 1.0</a> (the classic)
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/xpath/4.0/">Interactive XPath Expression Builder 4.0</a> (all new and improved)
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note that you'll need <b>IE5+</b> and <b>MSXML 3.0</b> for these to work, due to the heavy client-side scripting.
</p>
<p>
If you're forgetful like me and have no idea what to type, start with "Invoices/Invoice". MSDN has the best <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/xmlsdk/html/xmrefxpathexamples.asp">XPath syntax examples</a> and <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/xmlsdk/html/xmrefxpathexamples.asp">reference pages</a>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2004-12-17T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/interactive-xpath-expression-builder/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
