<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Google-fu</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/google-fu/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><img align="right" alt="Assalama Alaikum!" class="at-xid-6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fb2fe970c" height="393" hspace="5" src="https://blog.codinghorror.com/content/images/uploads/2005/05/6a0120a85dcdae970b0128776fb2fe970c-pi.jpg" vspace="5" width="198">
<p>
Did you ever get the feeling that <b>the browser address bar is the new command line?</b> I keep forgetting how much functionality Google provides in their search text box; I was reminded when <a href="http://damienkatz.net/">Damien Katz</a> posted a link to a nice little <a href="http://www.google.com/help/cheatsheet.html">Google search cheat sheet</a>. Google also automatically recognizes certain strings, such as UPS tracking numbers, UPC codes, math calculations, etcetera. Here's a <a href="http://www.googleguide.com/shortcuts.html">list of those shortcuts</a>, with helpful examples. There's also a <a href="http://www.googleguide.com/advanced_operators.html">more comprehensive list</a> of supposedly undocumented (at least on Google's web site) search operators. Interestingly, I found another list with at least one operator I've been looking for-- date range-- which doesn't appear at all on the other list:
</p>
<p>
</p>
<ol type="a">
<br>
<li> <b>link:url</b> Shows other pages with links to that url.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>related:url</b> same as "what's related" on serps.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>site:domain</b> restricts search results to the given domain.
<br>
</li>
<li>
<b>define:word</b> provides a definition of the word.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>allinurl:</b> shows only pages with all terms in the url.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>inurl:</b> like allinurl, but only for the next query word.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>allintitle:</b> shows only results with terms in title.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>intitle:</b> similar to allintitle, but only for the next word. "intitle:webmasterworld google" finds only pages with webmasterworld in the title, and google anywhere on the page.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>cache:url</b> will show the Google version of the passed url.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>info:url</b> will show a page containing links to related searches, backlinks, and pages containing the url. This is the same as typing the url into the search box.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>spell:</b> will spell check your query and search for it.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>stocks:</b> will lookup the search query in a stock index.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>filetype:</b> will restrict searches to that filetype. "-filetype:doc" to remove Microsoft word files.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>daterange:</b> is supported in Julian date format only. 2452384 is an example of a Julian date.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>maps:</b> If you enter a street address, a link to Yahoo Maps and to MapBlast will be presented.
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>phone:</b> enter anything that looks like a phone number to have a name and address displayed. Same is true for something that looks like an address (include a name and zip code)
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>site:www.somesite.net "+www.somesite.+net"</b>
<br>
(tells you how many pages of your site are indexed by google)
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>allintext:</b> searches only within text of pages, but not in the links or page title
<br>
</li>
<li> <b>allinlinks:</b> searches only within links, not text or title
<br>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
I've always wanted to query Google for web pages created or modified earlier than a certain date, but <a href="http://aa.usno.navy.mil/data/docs/JulianDate.html"><i>Julian</i></a> dates? Ugh! Well, at least someone already built a <a href="http://www.faganfinder.com/google.html">special Google search page</a> to get around this limitation.
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-05-19T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/google-fu/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
