<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Revisiting 7-ZIP</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/revisiting-7-zip/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>In my previous post, I <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000798.html">extolled the virtues of WinRAR and the RAR archive format</a>. I disregarded <a href="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-ZIP</a> because it didn't do well in <a href="http://www.maximumcompression.com/data/summary_mf3.php">that particular compression study</a>, and because my previous experiences with it had shown it to be <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000313.html">efficient, but brutally slow</a>.</p>
<p>But that's no longer true. Consider the following test I just conducted:</p>
<ul>
<li>Two files: a 587 MB virtual hard disk file, and a 11 KB virtual machine file.
</li>
<li>Test rig is a Dual Core Athlon X2 4800+.
</li>
<li>All default GUI settings were used.
</li>
<li>All extracting and archiving done from one physical hard drive to another, to reduce impact of disk contention.
</li>
</ul>
<table width="600px">
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right">Extraction</td>
<td align="right">Compression</td>
<td align="right">Size
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WinRAR 3.70 beta 2</td>
<td align="right">0:39</td>
<td align="right">3:09</td>
<td align="right">135 MB
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7-ZIP 4.20</td>
<td align="right">-</td>
<td align="right">6:04</td>
<td align="right">127 MB
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7-ZIP 4.44 beta</td>
<td align="right">0:40</td>
<td align="right">3:03</td>
<td align="right">125 MB
</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p><b>7-ZIP performance has doubled over the last two years.</b> And it's slightly more efficient at compression, too. That's impressive.</p>
<p>Performance is no longer a reason to choose WinRAR over 7-ZIP. Granted, this is a sample size of one, a single test on a single machine, but it's hard to ignore the dramatic reversal of fortune.</p>
<p>I still like WinRAR's ultra-slick shell integration. But 7-ZIP is a viable competitor now in terms of raw clock time performance, and as always, it tends to produce smaller archives than RAR. This more than addresses my previous criticisms. Mea culpa, 7-ZIP.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2007-02-23T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/revisiting-7-zip/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
