<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Coding Horror</title>
<description>programming and human factors</description>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
<!-- other elements omitted from this example -->
<item>
<title>Custom wsdlHelpGenerator + webroot = error</title>
<link>https://blog.codinghorror.com/custom-wsdlhelpgenerator-webroot-error/</link>
<content>
                <!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>
Why are the smallest bugs in the .NET framework always the most disproportionately frustrating? Take the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/cpgenref/html/gngrfwsdlhelpgenerator.asp">wsdlHelpGenerator</a> element, for example. Sure, it seems straightforward enough; you want to replace the default crappy, <b>random hash sorted list of Web Service methods with one that's (shock!) in alphabetical order</b>. I know, it's crazy talk, but bear with me. So you'd...
</p>
<ol>
<li>Make a copy of the <code>C:WINDOWSMicrosoft.NETFrameworkv1.1.4322CONFIGDefaultWsdlHelpGenerator.aspx</code> file
</li>
<li>Rename that file to <code>CustomWsdlHelpGenerator.aspx</code> and place it in the root of your Web Service solution
</li>
<li>Open the file and make a simple one-line modification, replacing <code>Hashtable methodsTable</code> with <code>SortedList methodsTable</code>
</li>
<li>Modify your <code>Web.config</code> to include the following:
</li>
</ol>
<p>
</p>
<pre language="xml">
&lt;webServices&gt;
&lt;wsdlHelpGenerator href="CustomWsdlHelpGenerator.aspx" /&gt;
&lt;/webServices&gt;
</pre>
<p>
And it works great! Well, as long as you deploy your Web Service to a subfolder under the webroot (eg, <a href="http://staging.company.com/mywebservice/">http://staging.company.com/mywebservice/</a>). However. If you deploy this very same code to a root URL (eg, <a href="http://mywebservice.company.com/">http://mywebservice.company.com/</a>, you get this exciting, ultra-fatal error:
</p>
<blockquote>
Configuration Error
<p>
<b>Description:</b> An error occurred during the processing of a configuration file required to service this request. Please review the specific error details below and modify your configuration file appropriately.
</p>
<p>
<b>Parser Error Message:</b> Exception in configuration section handler.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
This makes deploying to production a lot more, uh, <i>thrilling</i> than it would otherwise be. Commenting the <code>wsdlHelpGenerator</code> line out "fixes" the problem. So does moving the webservice to a subfolder under the root.
</p>
<p>
This egregious bug in the .NET framework really pisses me off, particularly since it has persisted into 1.1 SP1. I can find <a href="http://groups-beta.google.com/groups?q=wsdlhelpgenerator%20error">lots of people complaining about this in Google Groups</a>, but I can't find <i>one single workaround</i>. Can you? Class? Bueller? Bueller?
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown-->
            </content>
<pubDate>2005-04-07T12:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
<guid>https://blog.codinghorror.com/custom-wsdlhelpgenerator-webroot-error/</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
